<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lamentation over the dead in Christ, not as those without hope; with instruction, admonition, and encouragement to the survivers As it should have been delivered to the people (had not Satan hindered) at the funeral of Mr. Henry Rix of Cambridge, Jan. 19. 1656--7. in pursuance of his earnest request on his deathbed. Now published for the benefit of those that will hear. By Thomas Moore junior.</title>
            <author>Moore, Thomas, Junior.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216352</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828084</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828084</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32511</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51257)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32511)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1855:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lamentation over the dead in Christ, not as those without hope; with instruction, admonition, and encouragement to the survivers As it should have been delivered to the people (had not Satan hindered) at the funeral of Mr. Henry Rix of Cambridge, Jan. 19. 1656--7. in pursuance of his earnest request on his deathbed. Now published for the benefit of those that will hear. By Thomas Moore junior.</title>
                  <author>Moore, Thomas, Junior.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by R.I. for Livewell Chapman, at the Crown in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32511:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LAMENTATION Over the Dead in Chriſt, not as thoſe without hope; with inſtruction, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, and encouragement to the Survivers.</p>
            <p>As it ſhould have been delivered to the People (had not Satan hindered) at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Henry Rix</hi> of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Jan. 19. 1656—7. in purſuance of his earneſt requeſt on his Death-Bed. Now publiſhed for the benefit of thoſe that will hear.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS MOORE</hi> junior.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> lamented over <hi>Jonathan.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>I am diſtreſſed for thee my brother <hi>Jonathan,</hi> very pleaſant haſt thou been to me, thy love to me was wonderful, paſſing the love of Women; how are the mighty fallen in the midſt of the Battel, and the Weapons of Warre periſhed? <bibl>2 Sam. 1. 25, 26, 27.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>And <hi>Jeremy</hi> lamented for <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and all the Singing-men, and Singing-women ſpeak of <hi>Joſiah</hi> in their Lamentations to this day, and made them an Ordinance in Iſrael. Behold, they are written in the Lamentations, <bibl>2 Chro. 35. 25.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>But I would not have you ignorant Brethren concerning them that are aſleep, that yee ſorrow not even as others that have no hope; for if we beleeve that Jeſus dyed, and roſe again, even ſo them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo which ſleep in Jeſus will God bring with him, <bibl>1 Theſſ. 4. 14, 15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>R. I.</hi> for <hi>Livewell Chapman,</hi> at the Crown in Popeſ-head Alley. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:32511:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32511:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader, and eſpecially to thoſe at, or near <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the ſad news of my dear Brothers Sickneſs to death, I went as ſoon as I could, if happily I might to have ſeen him, and that I might have been refreſhed together with him before his departure; but it pleaſed our gracious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the wiſe Diſpoſer of all things, in whoſe hands are all our lives, our times, and ways, to deny me of that, by ſpeeding another Viſitor (to him farre better) to take him away from the evil againſt which he had been long ſtriving, in the light and ſtrength of the Lord, that he may henceforth be with him, and at reſt from all his Labours and Combates, though yet waiting for the compleating of the Adoption, that is, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the Body, till the reſt of his Brethren have finiſhed their courſe as well as he. He departed the night before I got to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where I underſtood, That it was his earneſt requeſt on his Death-bed, that if I came in time, I ſhould be deſired (as from him) to give the people a word if Exhortation at his Funeral, and alſo that the Miniſter of the Pariſh, on his deſire was freely willing with it; on which conſiderations I conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to it, and knew not of any Blocks in the way until the time was almoſt come, that I ſhould have performed the will of the Deceaſed in this matter; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to which ſervice, apprehending from the fore-mentioned conſiderations, God calling me, and making the way hitherto clear enough, I was very ready to have offered my ſelf, notwithſtanding ſome reports, I know not how raiſed, of ſome Schollars threatning incivility to me, which I did not much credit, of at leaſt feared not, purpoſing by the grace of God not to reſiſt evil if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; and trusting in a greater power than that of man for protection. In ſome others thought it convenient to take me off, yet could I not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied without publiſhing what I then intended to have ſpoken, and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>1 I cannot but judge the removal of this Iſraelite indeed, and at ſuch a time, to be a ſad Correction and Judgement, eſpecially to the place, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple among whom he lived, he being one whoſe heart (through the grace of
<pb facs="tcp:32511:3"/>
God in Chriſt our Saviour, towards man) was fixed, truſting in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and walking in the hearty belief and acknowledgement of the truth of the Goſpel, and waiting for the hope of it, and thence filled with the conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning operation of the love of Chriſt perſwading men, and ſeeking the good of all by all means within his capacity, ſhining as a light in the world, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a crooked and perverſe Generation, holding forth the Word of Life in word and converſation; and how much as to theſe things he was alone is that place I ſpare to ſpeak, yet he through that grace of God that bringeth Salvation to all men, teaching us (as <hi>Tit. 2. 11, 12.</hi>) ſo demeaned himſelf, that he had a good report of all men, as well as eſpecially of the truth itſelf; for cleaving to which, though he had many adverſaries, chiefly of thoſe that ſometimes in ſome meaſure acknowledged, and rejoyced in the truth with him, but now have turned away their ears from it, and are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aſide to fables, yet they could finde nothing againſt him, but in the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of his God, and were made aſhamed, wherein they falſly accuſed his good converſation in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>2 That which follows was much ſet upon my ſpirit, as a very needful and ſeaſonable Inſtruction, and Admonition to the people there, and at that time; and I knew not but God by his providence called me thither at ſuch a time, for ſuch an end, though I could not but judge my ſelf moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to preſent it.</p>
            <p>3 Some that obſerved, could not but take notice of a great hand of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, with great diligence exerciſed to the hindring it.</p>
            <p>Therefore that I may both doe what in me lies to performe the deſire of the deceaſed, and alſo not to rebell against him that preſſed my ſpirit, to give my ſence of the meaning of the voyce of this providence, as by bringing to remembrance, and opening the Scriptures to my underſtanding, he gave it me, if peradventure any may be awakened by it, I here preſent it to view, and commit it and my ſelf to him, in whom I deſire to be Servant to all,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. MOORE.</signed>
               <dateline>From my houſe at <hi>Lynn,</hi> 
                  <date>Febr. 10. 1656 7.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:32511:3"/>
            <head>On the Subject of the following Diſcourſe upon the Death of <hi>Henry Rix.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>H</hi>ere haſt thou firſt a Paradox explained,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>vincing ſome have Righteouſneſs attained,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>evertheleſs this truth remains, there's none</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>ighteous in, as of themſelves, not one</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Y</hi>et in the Lord, and 'tis in him alone:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>ighteouſneſs and ſtrength ſome have, and they</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>n him are juſtified, and glory aye,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>X</hi>pecting ſtill its Crown of Immortality.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Henry in's Lot ſhall then with Chriſt affix,</l>
               <l>And we with Chriſt ſhall meet our Brother <hi>Rix.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Next we preſent thee with our cauſe of grief,</l>
               <l>Deſiring God from Heaven to ſend relief;</l>
               <l>He's gone in whom no guile, an Iſraelite;</l>
               <l>Is there in's ſtead left ſuch another Light?</l>
               <l>Then had we not ſuch cauſe as now to mone,</l>
               <l>Yet mourn we not as thoſe that hope have none:</l>
               <l>Firſt, in behalf of him that's faln aſleep,</l>
               <l>We have great cauſe to joy, and not to weep;</l>
               <l>For we beleeving Chriſt did Dye, and Riſe,</l>
               <l>Do know that with him he ſhall come likewiſe,</l>
               <l>And then poſſeſs with all the Saints the Crown,</l>
               <l>The righteous Judge ſhall give when he comes down;</l>
               <l>And in mean time he reſts in bleſſed peace,</l>
               <l>Where from his warres and labours he doth ceaſe,</l>
               <l>Then for our ſelves, our God, our Rock's alive,</l>
               <l>And will not fail at need us to releeve:</l>
               <l>Yet for our ſelves we have cauſe to lament,</l>
               <l>Yea ſure the Judgement is of large extent,</l>
               <l>And larger than to them that lay't to heart,</l>
               <l>Nor is't the leſs becauſe few feele the ſmart,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill our cauſe of lamentation's more,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:32511:4"/>To ſes the Children of the Spiritual Whore;</l>
               <l>Againſt the Heavens themſelves with ſport rejoyce,</l>
               <l>Not doubting to prevail with their ſtrange voyce.</l>
               <l>Reproaching now the poor that truſts in God,</l>
               <l>Becauſe afflicted with their Fathers Rod;</l>
               <l>But in due time God will ariſe, and then</l>
               <l>No place will be for theſe proud wicked men:</l>
               <l>In the great Judgement then they ſhall not ſtand,</l>
               <l>But ſhall be broken with a mighty hand;</l>
               <l>A little while, and then he will not ſtay,</l>
               <l>But come with all his Saints, O come away;</l>
               <l>Is it not yet the time to judge thy Flock,</l>
               <l>When as to outward means their powers do ſlack?</l>
               <l>Is there yet any left, ſhut up, or hid?</l>
               <l>Cauſe them t' appear, thy flock to help and rid;</l>
               <l>Make them more wiſe and ſtrong to doe exploits,</l>
               <l>Through thy good name to ſhew the deep deceits,</l>
               <l>So manifold of him whoſe name is Legion,</l>
               <l>That with us may remaine the pure Religion,</l>
               <l>And haſte the coming of that bleſſed day,</l>
               <l>In which thou wilt wipe all our tears away:</l>
               <l>In mean time, teach us to account and mind,</l>
               <l>Thy patience is Salvation to th' unkind;</l>
               <l>A pleaſure in their death, thou now haſt none,</l>
               <l>While yet thy grace brings them Salvation;</l>
               <l>Of thy mind make us more, as reading well</l>
               <l>Ith' greatneſs of thy love, thy terror ſell.</l>
               <l>Thence inſtantly with meekneſs praying them,</l>
               <l>Now to be reconciled unto him;</l>
               <l>That was made Sin, and Curſe for's all, that we</l>
               <l>The righteouſneſs of God in him might be.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. M. Junior.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32511:4"/>
            <head>A Lamentation over the dead in Chriſt, with Inſtruction, Admonition, and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Survivers, in ſome explication of the words of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 57. 1. as compared with other Scriptures.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Iſaiah 57. 1.</bibl>
               <q>The Righteous periſheth, and no man layeth it to heart, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful men are taken away, none conſidering that the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is taken away from the evil [to come.]</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words preſent us with a Two-fold matter of Lamentation, or cauſe of grief, doubled in the expreſſion of each part, to note the greatneſs of the Judgement, and to awake us to the more diligence to learn righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by it.</p>
            <p>1 That the Righteous periſheth, merciful men, or men of kindneſs, and godlineſs are taken away.</p>
            <p>2 That no man laies it to heart, none conſiders that the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is taken away from the evil. We read [<hi>to come</hi>] but thoſe two words being added by the Tranſlators, as appears by their different Character, may be left out in our reading, and the text without them, not only as fully takes in the truth expreſſed by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32511:5"/>
but is more ſignified, <hi>viz.</hi> That he is taken away from the evil, as well that preſent as that to come. The Inſtructions fully ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, and ſet before us in the words of this Lamentation are,</p>
            <p>1 That the periſhing of the righteous, the taking away of men of kindneſs, and godlineſs, is a ſad correction to the ſurvivers, which God would have ſo laid to heart, and conſidered by them.</p>
            <p>2 That when God ſo ſtrikes, and yet none lay to heart, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it, it is an evidence of wilful blindneſs, and great hardneſs in ſuch a people, and a ſign and fore-runner of greater Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>3 That even in theſe ſad Judgements there is ſpecial mercy, and choyſe bleſſedneſs to thoſe ſo taken away, and that to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered alſo, they are taken away from the evil; <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, from henceforth, yèa ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I That the periſhing of the Righteous is a ſad correction to the ſurvivers, which God would have ſo laid to heart, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by them; for our underſtanding and uſefulneſs of this, wee ſhall propound to conſideration, 1. Who are the Righteous, 2. In what ſence they may be ſaid to periſh, and when they ſo doe; and then ſhall further demonſtrate and explicate the Poſition.</p>
            <p>I Who are the Righteous and merciful men, or men of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or godlineſs, truly if men be conſidered as they are by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and firſt birth, as deſcended from <hi>Adam,</hi> or as they are in and of themſelves, or in what they may attain to by the will of fleſh, or will-wiſdome, and ſtrength of man, in whatever exerciſed, <hi>There is none righteous, or doth good, no not one,</hi> of all the naturall Children of <hi>Adam;</hi> they have all ſinned, and are come ſhort of the glory of God, they are become wholly ſinful, weak, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, they are dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, and children of wrath, as ſo conſidered, one as well as another, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 19-23. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 1, 2. By the Law is the knowledge of ſin in the beſt as well as in the worſt works of men, yea it diſcovers his whole nature over-ſpread with it, and therefore by the deeds of it ſhall no man be juſtified in the ſight of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 11. <hi>Pſal,</hi> 143. 2.</p>
            <p>There is only one man of all the Nature, even the man Chriſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32511:5"/>
Jeſus, that is in a proper and ſtrict ſence, Good, or Righteous, in and of himſelf, and for us, and he is none of the natural Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, nor naturally of man, but of God, (<hi>Mark</hi> 12. 18.) who alſo prepared for him a Body in our Nature, and of a Woman, by the ſecret and wonderful efficacy of his holy Spirit, and did in that Body deliver him to Death for our Offences, and raiſe him again for our Juſtification; and gave him glory, that our faith and hope might be in God; And he is expreſly called the Righteous, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 1. the Juſt, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 6. even the righteous, or juſt one, and juſtly too; for,</p>
            <p>1 He is perfectly ſo in and of himſelf, being the Natural and only begotten Son of God, ſo that he is of the Father, the ſame that the Father is, Righteouſneſs, Juſtice, Truth, Holineſs, and Goodneſs it ſelf; yea in that Body prepared for him in mans Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though he was made in the likeneſs of ſinful fleſh, ſubject to all our infirmities that came by ſin, yet without ſin, <hi>He knew no ſin;</hi> And this rendred him a meet and worthy Perſon to undertake for Sinners, to prepare, and give a Ranſome to God, and bee a Mediator for them; for, <hi>Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean, not one;</hi> therefore no meer man can redeeme his Brother, or give to God a ranſome for him; for ſuch a High Prieſt became us, who is holy, harmleſs, undefiled, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>2 He is perfectly ſo in what he hath undertaken, and done for men in that Body prepared for him in mans Nature, he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly and voluntarily fulfilled that will of the Father he came to doe, as to the works to be finiſhed in his own Body on the earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 6 - 9. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10, 5 - 12. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 4. <hi>He humbled himſelf, and became obedient to death, even the death of the Croſs.</hi> He laid down his life that he might take it again, even as he received Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of his Father, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 7, 8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. 17, 18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12, 2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 24. and becauſe of this,</p>
            <p>3 He is made perfect for us, the Righteous, and juſt one, or juſtified Perſon in our Nature, and for us, acquit off all our treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes and ſins that were imputed to him, and ſo therein a Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer over all Curſe, and Death laid upon him, having by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf purged our ſins, he is accepted, and ſet down on the right hand of God as a perfect Ranſome, and price of Redemption for men, and ſtanding propitiation for the ſins of the whole world, yea a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32511:6"/>
Prince and Saviour, for to give repentance, and forgiveneſs of ſins, and the Judge of all, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3, 4, &amp; 12. 2. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5, 6. 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 2. 1, 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 31. &amp; 10. 36. 42. Yea,</p>
            <p>4 He is righteous and faithful in all appointed him. A faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Mediator and High Prieſt, a faithful teſtimony of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to men in due time, that through him they might be ſaved; and the Author of eternal Salvation to them that obey him, and the righteous Judge of quick and dead, by whom God ſhall judge the world in righteouſneſs, even by that man whom he hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, whereof he hath given aſſurance unto all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead, for to this end he dyed, roſe, and revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that he might be Lord of dead and living; ſo that hee is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and abſolutely the righteous One in and of himſelf, and for us; the Lord our righteouſneſs, in whom, and in whom only wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have righteouſneſs, and ſtrength; yet is not he the righteous that are here ſpoken of. For</p>
            <p>1 This Text ſpeaks in the plural number, of righteous ones, merciful men, men of kindneſs, or godlineſs, nor is he included as one of the righteous ones here ſpoken of. For</p>
            <p>2 He was not, nor could be holden of Death, as <hi>David,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that ſleep in Jeſus, are; his fleſh ſaw no corruption, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 10. with <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 25 - 31. ſo that he did not periſh out of the earth by death as they, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7. 1, 2. <hi>He was raiſed again the third day, and after ſeen of many witneſſes.</hi> Yea,</p>
            <p>3 Though he was taken from the earth in his Aſcenſion, yet that was no chaſtiſement, or correction, and ſo no cauſe of grief or ſorrow to us, no nor to them that did enjoy his perſonal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence on the earth; but cauſe of great joy, for if hee had not ſo perſonally aſcended to the Father. The Comforter, that coming forth of the Spirit of truth, in the evidence and demonſtration of the works finiſhed in his Body, accepted, and for ever vertuous with the Father for us, could not have come, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7. 39. &amp; 14. 26 - 28. &amp; 16. 7, 8. yea he went to prepare places for us, that he might come again Perſonally, and receive us to himſelf, that we, even all that by him beleeve in God, might be ever with him in his glory, <hi>Job.</hi> 14. And ſo neither is he ſo periſhed from the earth, or from among men, in his being perſonally received up into glory, as to be no more capable of converſing with them, helping, or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32511:6"/>
them good, but is thereby abſolutely perfected in ſuch capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, even in that body in mans nature through ſufferings glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for being aſcended farre above all heavens, even in Heaven it ſelf, there to appear in the preſence of God for us, even the ſame that deſcended into the lower parts of the earth; he fills all things with his influences, and operations, and is in his gracious and Spiritual preſence, and vertues, in the hearts and ſocieties of his people, that through grace beleeve in him, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 7. 8 - 10. 11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 17, 18.</p>
            <p>By all which it appears, he is none of the righteous ſpoken of in this text, yet the conſideration already propounded of him as the righteous one, will help us to underſtand who are the righteous that are here ſpoken of, and therefore is no digreſſion from our buſineſs; for from theſe two conſiderations, <hi>viz.</hi> That of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Race, or Children of <hi>Adam,</hi> there is none in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or in any thing they can doe, righteous, or that doth good, nor that is ſo accepted, owned, and juſtified in the ſight of God, no not one; and that he, and he only in mans Nature is the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous one, and that for us alſo, <hi>The Lord our Righteouſneſs;</hi> I ſay, from theſe two conſiderations, it appears;</p>
            <p>That of all the Children of men, they only are righteous that in the light and power of Gods teſtimony concerning Chriſt, doe ſo beleeve and receive it, that in belief and acknowledgement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they diſowne and run out of themſelves into Chriſt, for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and life, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 3 - 9.</p>
            <p>It is a good deſcription, or character of the righteous, that on hearing of the Name of the Lord, that it is a ſtrong tower, they as men therein made ſenſible of it, acknowledge their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, and the lyingneſs of other refuges, and therefore the danger of abiding out of this, they run into the Name of the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. 10. they fly for refuge (even in the light and powerful drawing of the Name, and Grace of God in Chriſt, which bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Salvation to all men in due time) unto the hope ſet before them in Chriſt, that they may lay hold of that, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 18.</p>
            <p>The righteous then are they (whoever they be, or whatever they have been) that through his name beleeve in him, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 35. 43. for what ſaith the Scripture? <hi>Abraham beleeved God, and it was counted to him for righteouſneſs;</hi> now to him that worketh is the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32511:7"/>
reward not reckoned of Grace, but of Debt; but to him that worketh not, but beleeveth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteouſneſs, for that was not written for his ſake alone that it was imputed to him; but for us alſo, to whom it ſhall be imputed, <hi>if we beleeve on him that raiſed up Jeſus our Lord from the dead, who was delivered for our effences, and raiſed againe for our juſtification,</hi> Rom. 4. 3, 4, 5. 23, 24, 25. <hi>For with the heart man beleeveth unto righteouſneſs,</hi> chap. 10. 10. Therefore even the ſinners of the Gentiles, which before followed not after righteouſneſs, yet when the light of Gods teſtimony concerning Chriſt came to them, they falling down in the acknowledgement of their own vileneſs as therein diſcovered, and ſeeking righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by faith in Chriſt attained righteouſneſs; when <hi>Iſrael</hi> which followed after the Law of Righteouſneſs yet attained it not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſought it not by faith, but as it were by the works of the Law, for they being ignorant of Gods Righteouſneſs, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to eſtabliſh their own, have not ſubmitted themſelves to the righteouſneſs of God, for Chriſt is the end of the Law for righteouſneſs to every one that beleeveth; for <hi>Moſes</hi> deſcribeth the righteouſneſs which is of the Law, that the man which doth theſe things ſhall live by them, according to which rule there ſhal no man be juſtified in the ſight of God; for by the Law is the knowledge of ſin, yea it concludes under the Curſe, <hi>Every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> that continueth not in all that is written in the book of the Law to doe it, Gal.</hi> 3. 10, 11, 12. ſo that whoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 10. and there is not a juſt man upon earth that doeth good, and ſinneth not, <hi>Eccleſ. 7. 20. yea, la many things we offend all,</hi> Jam. 3. 2. But the righteouſneſs which is of faith ſpeaketh on this wife, <hi>Say not in thy heart, who ſhall aſcend into heaven,</hi> that is, to bring down from above, <hi>or who ſhall deſcend into the deep,</hi> that is, to bring up Chriſt again from the dead; it ſets not men a work to enquire how theſe things ſhell bee wrought for them in Chriſt, or to fancy, or ſeek for an accompliſhment of them over again in them. But what ſaith it, <hi>The Word is nigh thee, even that preaching of peace by Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> declaring all this freely done, and finiſhed for us by God in the Perſon of Chriſt, without any thought, motion, or deſire of ours; <hi>This word of Reconciliation is nigh thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart;</hi> even this word of faith which wee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32511:7"/>
preach, declaring the ground of Faith prepared, and true in him, and thence inſtructing and perſwading to beleeve it. This is made nigh in thoſe preachings of it vouchſafed, that by its owne light and power it might bee acknowledged, and beleeved, that if ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording, as in this nigh coming of the Word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> light and power comes with it, inſtructing, moving, and ſtrengthening the heart, thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth, and beleeve in thine heart, that God hath raiſed Chriſt from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved, for with the heart man beleeveth unto righteouſneſs, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 30-33. &amp; 10. 1-11. therefore alſo this Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> interprets the true fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers after righteouſneſs to bee they that ſeek the Lord, for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and ſtrength, that on the report of his righteouſneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near in Chriſt, in whom he hath cauſed his Judgement to reſt for a light to the people, doe beleeve that report, and entertaine in their heart that his Law, or Doctrine, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51. 1-7. &amp; 45. 22-25, &amp; 53. 1.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that in the light and power of Gods teſtimony concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſt, in the opening of it to them, as therein it is made nigh them, fall down in the ſence and acknowledgement of their owne ſinfulneſs, and vileneſs, and the unprofitableneſs of all their owne works to help them, and ſeek righteouſneſs in Chriſt, even by faith in him, in what hee hath done, and is become for ſinners, that through the knowledge and faith of him they may bee found in him, clothed with his Righteouſneſs, and not that of their own, <hi>Phil. 3, 8, 9, 10. 1 Job.</hi> 5. 20. Theſe are the righteous, and ſo of the righteous Nation, that learneth and keepeth the truth as it is in Jeſus; theſe are the righteous ſpoken of in this text, and therefore truly ſo called.</p>
            <p>1 Becauſe herein they doe Righteouſneſs, or Juſtice, they are doers, or workers of good, <hi>Rom. 2. 10. Acts 10. 35. 43. 1 Joh.</hi> 2. 18, 29. &amp; 3. 6. 2 <hi>Joh. 9. 3. Joh.</hi> 11. For,</p>
            <p>1 In this they doe nothing in any light, wiſdome, or ſtrength of theirs as of them, in or by which no man can underſtand the things of the Spirit, or come to Chriſt, or doe good, but as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſtrength is to ſit ſtill in this reſpect, letting their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations fall, and every high thing that exalts it ſelf againſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of Chriſt; they by him do beleeve in God, they through Grace beleeve, and that not of themſelves, but of the gift of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32511:8"/>
God, they come in his drawings; ſee light, not in their own, but in his light, beleeve in the evidence and demonſtration of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and by the power thereof coming along to them in his words, and works, ſo that their faith is of the operation of God, who of the diſcovery of his owne good will in Chriſt, through the word of truth begets them; they are in this not their owne, but his Workmanſhip created in Chriſt Jeſus, who of God is made to them Wiſdome, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification, and Redemption, and ſo doe work the work of God, not only which hee requires of them, but which himſelf is working in them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 29. for they are born to this beleeving on his name, not of bloud, nor of the will of fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of God, <hi>Joh. 1. 12, 13. 1 J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. 5. 1. Jam. 1. 18, 19. 1 Cor. 1. 29, 30. Eph.</hi> 2. 10. and yet this is graciouſly imputed, or counted to them for righteouſneſs, though it is the powerful operation of the grace of God in them through his name. As on the other hand, that which is in Scripture called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief,</hi> that is, to reject when men hear, is truly charged on men as their owne proper ſin, diſobedience, and unrighteouſneſs, even wilfully committed againſt the light and power of Gods grace bringing Salvation, for though men have neither light of underſtanding, nor freedome, or inclination of will in themſelves as of themſelves, yet while he is calling hee is certainly putting forth his hand, drawing with the cords of love, and the bands of a man, the demonſtrations of his love, evidenced in the lifting up the Son of Man, and lifting up the yoke of thraldome on the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſetting meat before them; ſo that his goodneſs not only hath ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, but ſutable operation in it. It doth lead men to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance though they draw back, and harden their hearts again, ſo that he that deſpiſeth, deſpiſeth not man only, but God, who hath alſo given them of his holy Spirit to inſtruct and reprove them; they harden their hearts againſt the word ſpoken in his Spirit, in the light and power of that by his Prophets, <hi>Iſa. 65. 1, 2. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 11. 2-7. Rom. 2. 4, 5. Nehem. 9. 20. 26. Zach. 9. 11, 12. 1 Theſſ.</hi> 4. 8. and ſo are fighters againſt God, cloſing their eyes, and ſtopping their ears, and hardening their hearts when hee is opening, and working upon them, leſt they ſhould be converted, and hee ſhould heal them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32511:8"/>2 They doe in this, beleeving on his name, doe nothing but what they have good reaſon and ſubſtantial ground for, in what he hath done, and is become for them, as declared in his teſti-Mony, and what they are thence obliged to as their reaſonable ſervice, there being a righteous ground and foundation of faith prepared and laid for us in Chriſt, as declared in the Goſpel, whether men beleeve, and ſo come and be built upon it or no; for <hi>God hath made him that knew no ſin, to be ſin for us, that wee might hee made the righteouſneſs of God in him.</hi> Whence alſo the Holy Ghoſt reproves the world of ſin, becauſe they beleeve not on Chriſt, and evidences it to be great unrighteouſneſs, from the conſideration of what great things he hath done for them, as alſo from the faithful evidences thereof to them, inſtructing and moving to it, as their reaſonable ſervice; ſo that indeed they render him hatred for his love, and evil for his good will, and are without cauſe his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, yea againſt, and contrary to all right reaſon, or cauſe, <hi>They not regarding the work of the Lord, nor the operation of his hands,</hi> which was true in him for and towards them, that through him they might have beleeved, <hi>Joh. 16. 8. 14. 1 Sam. 12. 24, 25. Pſal. 68. 18-21. 2 Corinth. 5. 11-21. &amp; 6. 1, 2. Pſal.</hi> 28. 5. &amp; 109. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>3 This work of faith in Jeſus is a righteous work, directed in truth, as may be ſeen in every act or branch of this faith of the operation of God. For,</p>
            <p>1 Such it is, as in which they acknowledge God to be true in his teſtimony concerning Chriſt, which is the great things of his Law; and in all the inſtructions and ſayings thereof, and therein acknowledge, and diſown themſelves, and all their own imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the traditions of men, as diſcovered, and detected in the light of Gods teſtimony, to be vanity and lyes; he that hath received his teſtimony, hath ſet to his Seal that God is true; whereas on the other hand, hee that beleeveth not God, hath made him that is the God, &amp; Fountain of all truth, a Lyar, <hi>becauſe he beleeveth not the record that God gave of his Son, even this record, that God hath given us eternal life in his Son,</hi> ſo as to bee received in receiving him, in his teſtimony, &amp;c. <hi>Joh. 3. 33. 1 Joh.</hi> 5. 10-12. What greater unrighteouſneſs than to make God a Lyar, and yet this is done by all, that when they hear, beleeve not the record of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32511:9"/>
God concerning Chriſt; but in the faith of Gods operation, God is acknowledged to be true, and every man a lyar; his Word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as his, and reverenced and preferred before all the Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Precepts of men, if never ſo many, and thoſe never ſo learned, or holy.</p>
            <p>2 Such it is, as in which they aſcribe righteouſneſs to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and make their boaſt of his righteouſneſs, and of his only, <hi>Job 36. 2, 3. Pſal.</hi> 71, 15, 16. As that in which Law is anſwered, Truth fulfilled, a Door of approach to God opened, and without which they muſt have been for ever caſt out, as an uncleane thing, ſo as in this they acknowledge their owne ſinfulneſs, and vileneſs, as therein evidenced. They are the true confeſſors of ſins, that doe in the belief of that teſtimony of God concerning Chriſt, owne them as theirs, according to the diſcoveries of the true Light, and ſo confeſs, and diſowne, and give them up as filthy, as thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected to be purged; and ſuch confeſſion and acknowledgement of our owne vileneſs is certainly included in this faith of the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God; If a man with the heart beleeve Gods teſtimony concerning Chriſt, then doth he therein beleeve what it faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning himſelf, or concerning Sin, or Righteouſneſs to bee true, and ſo beleeving, ownes its reproofs, whence the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> faith, <hi>If we,</hi> any of thoſe great Apoſtles, and ſo conſequently any belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in this life, <hi>ſay, we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us; If we ſay that we have not ſinned, we make him a Lyar, and his word is not in us,</hi> 1 Joh. 1. 8. 10. If any object againſt the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of this act of faith, That it is affirmed of <hi>Zacharias</hi> and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> that <hi>they were both righteous before God, walking in all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Lord blameleſs,</hi> to this we anſwer; This confirms what we have already ſaid, for if they walked in all the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the Lord blameleſs, then they walked in this of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing our ſins, always acknowledging our owne vileneſs, and wretchedneſs. And truly this was contained in all thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and Ordinances of the Law, under which he ſerved in the Prieſts Office, for in thoſe Sacrifices there was a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance againe of ſins every year, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 3. yea the High Prieſt himſelf ought, as for the people, ſo alſo for himſelf to offer for ſin 8, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 3. And now the prefect Sacrifice is offered, and the Purgation for all Sins compleatly made in the vertue of the bloud
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32511:9"/>
of Chriſt, men are in the teſtimony of this Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>untainepened, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to be ſinners, and all their righteouſneſs as filthy raggs, and ſo their owne vileneſs, and the need of coming to this Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains for waſhing, always ſhewed in the opening of it; ſo that he that walks not in the confeſſion, or acknowledgement of his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, vileneſs, and wretchedneſs, as there diſcovered, aſcribing righteouſneſs only to his Maker; he doth not righteouſneſs, hee makes God a Lyar, the truth is not in him; hee walks not blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; for by the deeds of the Law ſhall no man be juſtified as blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in the ſight of God, for all have ſinned, and are ſinners, have Sin in them, as well as Death upon them, while in this mortal bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, rendring it vile and wretched, <hi>Phil. 3. laſt. Rom.</hi> 7. 18-24. And for a ſinner to hide his ſin is moſt worthy of blame; the juſt are they that live by faith in the righteouſneſs of another, even of Jeſus Chriſt, the juſt and righteous one. Behold, his Soul which is lefted up, is not upright in him, <hi>Galath. 3. 11, 12. Rom. 1. 16, 17. Hab.</hi> 2. 4. Hence the confeſſing of our ſins anſwers to, and is put for the walking in the light, as he is in the light, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 7. 9. and good reaſon, for God is always in the diſcovery and demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt the true light, diſcovering our ſinfulneſs, and vileneſs, that we may not truſt in our ſelves, but receive the ſentence of Death there, that we may learn in the beleife and mindfulneſs of his teſtimony, concerning Chriſt, to truſt in him that raiſeth the dead. So that if we bee walking in the light, beleeving and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging Chriſt in his teſtimony, we muſt needs be found in the beleeving view, and remembrance of what he hath done, and is become for us, and Gods glory in him confeſſing our ſins; and ſo he that is borne of God, that is led of the Spirit of God that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways leads into, and in Chriſt, for all righteouſneſs and life; though he have ſin in him (for which ſimply God holds no man underblame, or Condemnation by Chriſt) yet ſo farre forth as he is born of God, that is, as he abideth in Chriſt he ſinneth not, hee doth not commit or ſerve ſin, no not in hiding his ſins, which is the firſt ſtep of making proviſion for it, which who ſo doth, ſhall not proſper; truly he ſhould ſin with a very high hand, even to the making God a Lyar, if he ſhould ſay that hee had no ſin in him, warring, and moveing for ſervice, or that he had not ſinned; yea doubtleſs, in any thing wherein his heart is departing from his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32511:10"/>
or his eye wandring into corners; the immortal Seed, the Word of God not retained in his heart, in beleeving mindfulneſs, Sin gets the advantage of him, and his readineſs to halt appears, and ſo <hi>in many things we offend all,</hi> and are therein of Satan, not of God, 1 <hi>Joh. 3. 5, 8-10. Pſal. 38. 17, 18. Prov. 28. 13, 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pſa.</hi> 19. 12, 13. &amp; 119. 8. 11. 133. 176. &amp; 51. 1-7.</p>
            <p>3 Such alſo is this beleeving with the heart, that God hath raiſed Chriſt from the Dead, that in it, the Lord himſelf becomes the Beleevers hope, his expectation of all further grace and glory is in him, begot, and ſtrengthened from the infinite grace of God to man ward, commended in this, that while we were ſinners, and enemies, in due time Chriſt dyed for us, and the infinite vertue of his Bloud, in which the peace and attonement was made with God for us, while we were yet enemies; This grace in Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved renders him precious, fills the heart with high eſteeme of the greatneſs, and truth of Gods love in him, and of the infinite and abiding vertue of his Bloud, and his fitneſs and faithfulneſs throught it, to perfect what concerns them. So that in this faith of Gods operation, their expectation and hope is not grounded, either on a peremptory concluſion, that they cannot fall, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, or on their act of beleeving, or faithfulneſs, and reſolutions of conſtancy, and abiding; nor are they left to draw up their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and hope, by way of Argument from their being ſuch, or in ſuch a ſtate, as to which ſuch Promiſes are made; but the grace in Chriſt underſtood, and beleeved, the heart being exerciſed in the hearty beleef and mindfulneſs of him; what he hath done, and is become for ſinners, and his office, faithfulneſs, and readineſs to help, teach, and draw them, and to accept all commers without up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding, and to give them through his name in the vertues, and openings of it, forgiveneſs of ſins, and eternal life, in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and faith of it, and firſt fruites of the Spirit now, and in the hope of the Harveſt in due time. I ſay, the heart and mind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exerciſed in the hearty belief, and mindfulneſs of this grace in Chriſt, and ſo ſtayed on his name, is not then left to reflect back into it ſelf, to draw up its conſolation, and hope, from its being ſuch a beleever, but is filled with ſtrong conſolation, and hope, through the grace underſtood and perceived in Chriſt; while the heart is only minding him that is the ground, and object
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32511:10"/>
of hope, the hope is begot, and ſtrengthened in a Divine and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual way, through the opening of that name, and ſhedding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad his love in the heart therein; ſo that Jeſus Chriſt received by faith in his teſtimony, and not their receit of him, is unto them, and in their hearts the hope of glory, the ground and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of it, and he from whom viewed it ſprings, and in whom it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And that after the ſame conſideration of him, as hee is in the Goſpel preached to every man; <hi>He that ſpared not his owne Sonne, but delivered him up for us all, how ſhall he not with him freely give us all things.</hi> See <hi>Rom. 5. 5-10. &amp; 8. 32. Col. 1. 26, 27. Gal. 2. 20. Joh.</hi> 6. 51. And ſuch is the truth and excellency of this name of God in Chriſt, that they that k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w it will truſt in it, if any man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever did know, own, liſten, and ſeek to it, according to the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of it brought him, it would beget truſt, and hope, of which he ſhould not be aſhamed; it quickens to new and living hope, through the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead.</p>
            <p>Again, in this faith of the operation of God their expectation is ſo in him, even of all things pertaining to life, and godlineſs to be now given, with him, not without him, or in any other way; but through the knowledge of him, whom he ſpared not, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up, for us all, that even that hope retained in them purifies their hearts from ways of iniquity, in which preſumptuouſly growing careleſs, or wandering from him, they might miſcarry, and fayl of the grace of God, ſo as they are inſtructed, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed by it to give diligence, and attend always to read the viſion of God, as written in the face of Chriſt, that ſo they may be ſtrengthened to run, and kept through faith, to the Salvation ready to be revealed in the laſt time. Yea ſuch it is, as from the excellency and grace in the ground of it, as alſo in the way in which it is to be met with, rather to bee choſen then any other way, or rule, and the excellent glory of the end of it, as ſtrengthens them to all patience and long ſuffering with joyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and as thoſe that beleeve in him, and look for ſuch things, not to make haſt, to fancy an accompliſhment of the great things hoped for in this day, or to bring about the accompliſhment of Gods promiſes, he that beleeves makes not haſt; Behold his ſoul, that is lifted up, either above the reading of the Viſion of God in Chriſt in his teſtimony given, for guiding his feet in the way of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32511:11"/>
peace, <hi>that he may run with patience the race ſet before him,</hi> as <hi>Heb.</hi> 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1, 2. or to imagine and boaſt of an enjoyment of the Viſion, ſo as by ſeeing and poſſeſſing the great things, the glory in the hope of which we are called by the Goſpel, or to put to his hand in ſtriving, and fighting for the haſting or bringing forth of Gods righteouſneſs in the things behind. His ſoul is not upright in him, but <hi>the juſt ſhall live by faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all which conſiderations it appears, they are in this bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving through his name, workers of righteouſneſs, doers of the truth, and therefore truly called, <hi>The righteous.</hi> As well as alſo,</p>
            <p>2 Becauſe they are herein juſtified in the ſight of God, imputed, accounted, and accepted righteous in that perfect righteouſneſs Chriſt hath wrought, and is become for them with which faith cloſeth. <hi>By the deeds of the Law ſhall no man be juſtified in the ſight of God;</hi> but now the righteouſneſs of God without the Law is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, being witneſſed by the Law and the Prophets, even the righteouſneſs of God by faith of Jeſus; that is, by the Preaching, or Doctrine of Jeſus: So now, manifeſted unto all, and upon all them that beleeve, unto all by way of redundancy, tender, and manifeſtation, but upon all that beleeve, even by way of imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it to them, and acceptation of them in it; ſo in the next Chapter, God is ſaid to impute righteouſneſs without works unto them, to accept their perſons into delightful favour, and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, by and in the vertue of that perfect righteouſneſs which they have by faith accepted, and ſo they are made accepted in the Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; they are made, or pronounced, and preſented good, juſt, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in the ſight of God, being found in him; and ſo it is upon all them that beleeve, for there is no difference, <hi>for all have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God, being juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Jeſus.</hi> That (<hi>verſ.</hi> 24.) anſwers to, and ſhews the reaſon of both the former branches, (<hi>viz.) That the righteouſneſs of God is unto all, and upon all them that beleeve, though all have ſinned, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo is to be underſtood in a two-fold ſence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 The whole Nature is juſtified in the ſecond man Chriſt Jeſus, that ſtood for all, to bear their ſins, in which all have already ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and with which the whole Nature is thence polluted, in that he is juſtified for them from the ſins imputed to him in his Reſurrection, and this is freely by his grace through the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32511:11"/>
in Jeſus. 2. All that beleeve, every one of them beleeving what he hath done, and is become for ſinners, and ſo through his Name beleeving on him, are in their particular perſons juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in him; God accepts them in his Son, and remembers not, nor doth impute to them their former wickedneſs, or preſent unprofitableneſs, but imputeth to them righteouſneſs without works; as in <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 35. 43. that ſaying, <hi>That in every Nation, he that feareth God, and worketh righteouſneſs, is accepted with him,</hi> verſ. 35. is thus explicated, as fulfilled among thoſe where the Goſpel comes, <hi>That through his name, whoſoever beleeveth on him ſhall receive the forgiveneſs of ſins,</hi> verſ. 43. So <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 39. <hi>By him all that beleeve are juſtified from all things, from which they could not be juſtified by the Law of Moſes, they are delivered from under the condemnation of the wrath, which in reſpect of the execution of it is yet to come, under which they all abide, that on hearing beleeve not on the Son of God,</hi> 1 Theſ. 1. 10. Joh. 3. 18. 36. He juſtifieth even the ungodly beleeving, and ſo coming to, and being found in the righteous one, <hi>that being juſtified freely by his grace, they might be more and more made heirs according to the hope of eternal life given us in Chriſt, that through the righteouſneſs of God, and our Saviour, they might be made to be meet partakers of the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the Saints in light,</hi> Rom. 3. 20-22-24 25, 26. &amp; 4. 3, 4, 5. Tit. 3. 4-7. And ſo,</p>
            <p>3 Therefore alſo are ſuch beleevers on his name called, <hi>The righteous,</hi> becauſe the end and fruit of this righteouſneſs of God, and our Saviour, in which beleeving they are accepted, is alſo, that through the knowledge and faith thereof the righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in them, even the righteous affections, and ſervices the Law required, but gave no ſtrength to bring forth, as well as the life and peace it was ordained to, but could not give; that the beleever might bee filled with the fruits of righteouſneſs by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rom. 8. 2, 3, 4. Phil.</hi> 1. 10, 11. even the fruites of the Spirit, whoſe evidence and demonſtration is of Chriſt, in his teſtimony, bringing forth in the beleeving receiver, <hi>love, joy, peace, long ſuffering, gentleneſs, goodneſs, faith, meekneſs, temperance</hi>—And they that are Chriſts, have in the light and ſtrength of the Lord, cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the fleſh with the affections and luſts, <hi>That henceforth they ſhould not ſerve ſin,</hi> Rom. 6. Gal. 5. They beleeving with the heart,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32511:12"/>
that God hath raiſed Chriſt from the dead, doe through the grace and power of that beleeved, and beleeved in, receive in a firſt fruits of the Spirit, the end of their faith, even the ſalvation of their ſouls, for with the heart man beleeveth unto righteouſneſs in this ſence alſo; <hi>Giving all diligence through the knowledge of him,</hi> they adde to, or in, their faith vertue; <hi>his goodneſſe, compaſſions, holineſſe, &amp;c.</hi> as manifeſted in Chriſt, frames to ſome likeneſſe, or conformity to him, <hi>in like love, bowels, mercies, holineſſe, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo in their vertue they adde, or proceed to further knowledge, taſtes, and proof of his graciouſneſſe, and therein temperance, and ſo <hi>godlineſſe, brotherly kindneſs, charity.</hi> Hence it is the Apoſtles would have theſe things, namely, <hi>the righteouſneſſe of God, and our Saviour, through which they were made partakers of ſuch precious and operative faith, to bee always bad in remembrance, ſeeing hereby they were ſaved, if they kept in memory</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 1-4. 2 Pet. 1. 1-12, &amp;c. <hi>this word of faith,</hi> and ſo this faith, that is of the operation of God is not without its works. It works through love, as from the conſideration of Gods love in Chriſt, as the foundation and fountaine of it, whence it hath all its freſh Springs, ſo in a channel of love towards God and man. It favours therefore of ignorance of the righteouſneſs of God, and our Saviour, and of the preciouſneſſe of this faith of Gods operation through it, when any ſay to us, That it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for us with the heart to beleeve, and cloſe with Gods teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony concerning Chriſt; but we muſt alſo look for the work of the Spirit inwardly, to quicken, ſave, and ſanctifie us; ſuch ſayings at leaſt ſignifie, that the work of the Spirit for quickning, ſaving, and ſanctifying the ſoul, is another thing beſides, and divided from this teſtimony, and not certainly met with in this way of beleeving, and having the heart and minde exerciſed and ſtayed on that name, and grace of his beleeved, ſo that a man may with his heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, and confeſſe, that God hath raiſed Chriſt from the dead, and yet not therein experiment the quickning and ſaving work of the Spirit; contrary to <hi>Rom. 10. 9, 10. 1 Cor.</hi> 15. and ſo doe indeed lead beleevers, having begun in the Spirit, to ſeek to bee made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by the fleſh. True it is, a man may ſay he hath faith, when yet his faith hath no works, nor ſpirit left in it, only an empty and idle opinionating ſuch a thing, or profeſſing to beleeve it as true, without any hearty mindfulneſſe of the importance, or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32511:12"/>
grace of the truth he pretends to cleeve. And of ſuch a faith <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Can it ſave? faith if it have no works is dead;</hi> a ſpiritleſſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable thing being alone, yea, even that faith is ſignified by him, to be nothing elſe but a dead Carcaſſe, pretence, outſide profeſſion, or ſhew of that which indeed is not, or not with the heart, not kept in beleeving remembrance and mindfulneſſe, for even there he ſignifies, that if it were unfeigned, or with the heart, according to the diſcoveries given, leſſe or more, it would work ſavingly, like as the ſame Propoſitions beleeved to be true by the Devils, works horror, becauſe they ſpeak as much againſt them, as they doe for man; even ſo man, any of mankind beleeving with the heart, it would be unto righteouſneſſe, <hi>Let God bee true, and every man a lyar;</hi> if any ſay, hee ſtedfaſtly, and with his heart beleeves the truth, and greatneſſe of Gods love to man ward, as manifeſted in Chriſt, and yet perceives no ſuch preciouſneſſe in Chriſt, and his teſtimony, as to move him according to his meaſure, <hi>to count all things but loſſe for the excellency of the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> but eaſily liſtens to, and admires the pretended excellencies of other ſpirits, that lift not up the Son of Man according to the Apoſtles Doctrine, but privily ſome other thing, or work in his ſtead, or embraces, and cleaves to the things of this preſent world, nor is moved with like love and compaſſion towards men from the grace in Chriſt beleeved, nor united in heart with them that fear his Name, and call upon him in truth, to know and own them as brethren, and ſtrive together with them for the faith of the Goſpel, but hath left his firſt Love, or elſe hath not yet ſo received the love of the truth as to ſave him; let us not acknowledge his ſayings to bee true, that he doth ſo unfeignedly beleeve the truth as it is in Jeſus, for ſo we ſhall render God a Lyar, and his Word without effect: but <hi>let God be true, and every man a Lyar,</hi> for that grace of God that bringeth ſalvation to all men, teacheth us, <hi>That denying ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, we ſhould live righteouſly, ſoberly, and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world, looking for that bleſſed hope, and glorious appearing of the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, and our Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let none of us therefore be moved to mean thoughts of the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of the word of faith, becauſe we, or others prove it not, while we think and ſay we beleeve, that thence we ſhould ſlight that as vain, and run to ſome other way to wait for the Spirit, or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32511:13"/>
for perfecting what was begun by the Spirit in the hearing of faith; but let us judge our ſelves of wavering, unconſtancy, or double<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> mindedneſſe, and of neglect of that ſo great Salvation, and having itching ears after ſomething ſutable to our divers luſts, and let us ſuffer our hearts by the grace of God, while yet admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing and ſtriving with us, to be more fixed truſting in the Lord, without guile or waveringneſſe, ſeeking righteouſneſſe in Jeſus, through the knowledge and faith of him, through which he gives all things pertaining to life and godlineſſe, <hi>Let us give more earneſt heed to the things we have heard, in the word of the truth of the Goſpel, leaſt at any time we let them ſlip.</hi> Conſider that love of God to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearing in and through Chriſt ſaved the Apoſtles, and ſo, and therein they had the waſhing of regeneration, and the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Holy Ghoſt ſhed on them abundantly through Jeſus Chriſt, and that Goſpel of Chriſt is the power of God to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to every one that beleeveth, for therein is the righteouſneſſe of God revealed from faith to faith, as it is written, <hi>The juſt ſhall live by faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to this anſwers the other deſcriptions of the righteous ones in this text; They are merciful men, or men of kindneſſe, or god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. Men filled and ſeaſoned, with the apprehenſion and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of the mercies, compaſſions, and kindneſſe of God to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to the unkind, and evil, and of that as diſcovered in the face of Chriſt, where he is to be truly known and worſhipped. And ſo of his good will in Chriſt, begotten through the word of truth, to their faith and hope in him, and joy in hope of the glory to bee revealed, and patience in tribulations, and thence moved and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with bowels and mercies, compaſſions; and kindneſſe, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to that they beleeve, and perceive to be in God towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, even towards all in blindneſſe and diſtreſſe, yea to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind and evil, the love of Chriſt conſtraining them, to perſwade them to be reconciled to God in Chriſt, and to ſeek <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir good by all means within their capacity, and with all earneſtneſſe, knowing alſo the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>errour of the Lord; becauſe they thus judge, <hi>That if one dyed for all, then were all dead, and that be dyed for all, that they which live ſhould not henceforth live to themſelves, but to him this dyed for them, and roſe again;</hi> yea hence alſo they are filled with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful love of, and deſire of fellowſhip with thoſe that call on the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32511:13"/>
name of the Lord out of a pure heart, and with bowels of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, humbleneſſe of mind, meekneſſe, and goodneſſeone towards another, and towards all men, anſwerable to the kindneſſe and mercies of God in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And ſo, if we read it, men of godlineſſe, it will come to the ſame, for they are the right and true worſhippers of God, <hi>who worſhip the Father in ſpirit and truth,</hi> and ſuch the Father ſeeks to worſhip him; they worſhip, adore, honour, magnifie, beleeve, and truſt in him, in the Spirit, that is, in the light and power of, and according to the teſtimony of Jeſus, and of Gods glory, as ſhined in his face; which teſtimony the Holy Ghoſt hath given, and in it, his evidence, and demonſtration of Chriſt, and of the Father, is. And therefore when we are called upon to godlineſſe, or to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, that teſtimony of Jeſus is ſaid to be the ſpirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, in, and according to which we are to worſhip, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 10. and ſo they in that light and ſtrength of the Spirit have their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in Chriſt Jeſus [<hi>The truth] And have no confidence in the fleſh,</hi> Joh. 4. 23, 24. &amp; 5. 23, 24. Phil. 3. 3. and in this true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and fear of the Lord, they are made partakers of the Divine Nature, in intereſt in it, union, or fellowſhip with it, conforming to it, ſo as by Chriſt through faith, ſo as thereby they goe on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging themſelves from all filthineſſe of fleſh, and ſpirit, perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting holineſſe in the fear of the Lord, 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 6. 16-18. &amp; 7. 1. purifying their hearts through beleef of the truth, and retaining the hope of it in them to unfeigned love of the brethren, and to more freedome from the intanglements, and cares of this world, as thoſe that are preſſing after the mark of the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus, which pure religion, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, brings forth its fruit, in their viſiting the Sick, the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and fatherleſſe in their affliction, and keeping themſelves unſpotted in the world; ſo as they walking in the Spirit (though they have fleſh warring in them) are by the light and power of the Spirit in the teſtimony of Jeſus, kept from fulfilling the luſts of the fleſh, and ſo preſerved blameleſſe unto the day of Chriſt, <hi>Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 8. 1-13. Gal.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>And to this agrees that two-fold deſcription of the Perſons that ſhall aſcend into the hill of the Lord, and ſtand in his holy place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24. 3, 4, 6. The firſt is, <hi>He that hath clean hands, and a pure
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32511:14"/>
hears, that hath not lift up his ſoul to vanity, nor ſworn deceitfully,</hi> for though <hi>there is none righteous, no not one,</hi> but <hi>all have ſinned, and are wholly polluted, and unclean,</hi> yet this truth remains for ever, <hi>Without holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord;</hi> ſo that if there be not ſome way in which men may be made again the righteouſneſs of God, and made partaker of his holineſs, they muſt all bee ſhut out for ever from God, under the curſe of the Law; but <hi>God hath made his Son that knew no ſin, to be ſin for us, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him;</hi> and according to that rule the ſixth verſe of that Pſalme gives us the next, and fundamental deſcription of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the glorious priviledge fore-mentioned, or rather the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of thoſe Perſons, in whom the truth of the former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription is found, and ſo an anſwer to the queſtion, <hi>Who are the righteous? This is the generation of them that ſeek him, that ſeek thy face O Jacob,</hi> or, O God of <hi>Jacob;</hi> that ſeek the Lord for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſtrength, that through his Name beleeving in him, ſeek righteouſneſſe by faith in Jeſus, as <hi>Iſa. 55. 3, 4, 5, 6. &amp; 45. 22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24, 25. Rom.</hi> 9. 30. and as before is ſhewed by the Scriptures, <hi>On them comes that bleſſedneſſe of Gods not imputing former iniquities, but imputing righteouſneſſe without works,</hi> Rom. 3. 25, 26. &amp; 4. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. yea they through the underſtanding and faith of Jeſus, have their hearts ſprinkled from an evil Conſcience, and their whole man in all their actings, and converſation, therein continually waſhed with that pure water of the love of God, through the blond of Chriſt ſhed abroad in their heart, <hi>Heb. 10. 19-22. 1 Pet.</hi> 1. 18-22. that in the iſſue they may be preſented without ſpot, or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing, <hi>Epheſ. 5. 26, 27. Col.</hi> 1. 21, 22, 23.</p>
            <p>And truly this large deſcription, and explication of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and merciful men, or men of kindneſs, and godlineſs, gives us a true character of him, whoſe being taken from us, occaſioned this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>We come in the next place to conſider.</p>
            <p>2 In what ſence they may be ſaid to periſh, and when they ſo doe. Here give me leave for our inſtruction and encouragement, Firſt, to propound to conſideration, in what ſence they periſh not; in reſpect of themſelves, or as with reference to their hope to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; <hi>They periſh not,</hi> they for their parts <hi>are not driven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, or cut off from God, or from their hope in death;</hi> the wicked dying
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32511:14"/>
in his ſins, even in his ſtubborn refuſall of him that came to ſave him from his ſins, and ſo out of Chriſt, he is therein driven away in his wickedneſs, cut off, and ſhut out from God, and from the hope of a better life, and from all opportunities of ever being made partaker of that hope; doth not their excellency which is in them, even their hope goe away, and periſh with them? They dye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wiſdome; <hi>But the righteous hath hope in his death;</hi> hee retaines, or holds his hope and joy even in death, yea then goes to a more full enjoyment of it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 32. Whence our Saviour ſaith, <hi>If a man keep my ſayings, he ſhall never ſee death;</hi> hee ſhall never dye, in the full, and proper ſence of the word, he ſhall not in, or by death be ſeparated, or cut off from God, or from his hope and portion in him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 51. &amp; 11. 26. but from thenceforth ſhall be more eſpecially bleſſed in, and with his preſence, and with more immediate, and uninterrupted fellowſhip with him in ſpirit, even while out of the body, and while that ſleeps in the duſt; whence the Apoſtle deſired, in reſpect of himſelf, much rather to depart out of the body, out of the fleſh, that he might enjoy that more immediate, and free preſence of, &amp; fellowſhip with Chriſt, which to him would be farre better, 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 1-6-8. Phil.</hi> 1. 20. 23. neither are their bodies though reſting in Death, and ſo ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the duſt of the earth, loſt, cut off, or periſhed, as indeed they ſhould be if there were no Reſurrection of the Dead, as the Apoſtle reaſons, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 18, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt be not raiſed, and ſo, <hi>If the dead riſe not, then thoſe which are fallen aſleep in Chriſt are periſhed; If in this life only we had hope in Chriſt, we were of all men moſt miſerable;</hi> then indeed there had been ſome ground for, and truth in their ſaying, <hi>Ezek. 37. 11. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdour bones are dryed, our hope is loſt, and we are cut off for our parts; for even thoſe that having ſeen thoſe great and precious promiſes afarre off, which were before confirmed of God in Chriſt, and were perſwaded of them: and embraced them, yet dyed, not having received them.</hi> But what ſaith the anſwer of God to them, <hi>verſ. 12. Behold O my people, I will open your Graves, and cauſe you to come up out of your Graves, and bring you into the Land of Iſrael, &amp;c.</hi> And now alſo for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our faith, the ground of it is actually come forth and manifeſted, <hi>Christ is riſen from the dead, and become the firſt fruits of them that ſleep, for ſince by man,</hi> even by the offence and diſobedience
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32511:15"/>
of one man, <hi>ſin,</hi> and ſo death by ſin, the firſt death <hi>reigneth on all men, and ſo it is appointed to the whole kind once to dye,</hi> though all ſhall not ſleep, or reſt in death, ſome of this Body of righteous ones, ſhall ſurvive at the Perſonal appearance of Chriſt in his glory, and they ſhall immediately, and on a ſudden bee changed, and paſſe through death, yet ſo as therein they ſhall dye, though not ſleep, or reſt in death; Death is paſſed on all in the ordinance and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of God, by reaſon of the Sin entring by one man, <hi>even ſo by man (viz.)</hi> by the obedience and righteouſneſs of one man, Jeſus Chriſt, in which the tranſgreſſion of the firſt one man, in which all have ſinned, and the ſin and ſinfulneſs thence entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and over-ſpreading the whole Nature, is ſo finiſhed, and made an end of in the Court of Heaven, or purged, and put away from before the Father, that no man ſhall eternally periſh, or bee ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from God in it; nor are they left under the power of that Judgement of Baniſhment, the curſe of the Law; but all Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment committed to the Son, and he impowred to execute Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo, becauſe he is the Son of Man; by him is the Aſſurance and certainty of the Reſurrection of the dead, <hi>For as in</hi> Adam <hi>all dye,</hi> even in the influence &amp; demerit, as the fruit of his tranſgreſſion; even ſo in Chriſt, in the merit, influence and vertue, and as the fruit of his Righteouſneſs <hi>ſhall all be made alive;</hi> raiſed out of the firſt Death, that they may all appear before his Judgement Seat, to be judged according to the rule of his Goſpel; all ſhall bee raiſed by him, but every man in his own order. Chriſt the firſt fruits being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready raiſed from the dead, afterwards, namely, immediately at the time of his ſecond Perſonal coming, thoſe that are his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar ones, the righteous Nation that keepeth the truth, thoſe in whoſe heart the Spirit of him that raiſed up Jeſus from the dead, (in that evidence, and demonſtration of him in his teſtimony) dwells, to the quickning their ſpirits now, or making them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live to God, while yet the body is dead becauſe of ſin, ſhall then have their mortal bodies quickned, even raiſed from the dead by the ſame ſpirit that now dwells in them; and ſhall then, in their ſouls, and bodies reunited in that bleſſed and glorious Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Juſt, enter together with him into the everlaſting poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the joy and glory of their Lord. And this is that which is called, <hi>The firſt Reſurrection,</hi> Rev. 20. 4 - 6. Theſſ. 4. 16. the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32511:15"/>
teſt of the Dead, <hi>John</hi> in that Viſion of things to come, ſaw, lived not again till the thouſand years of Chriſts Perſonal Reign on earth, with the children of the firſt Reſurrection were finiſhed.</p>
            <p>In which time there ſhall be new Heaven, and new Earth, and the new Jeruſalem come down from God out of Heaven, and all things made new, and a perfectly righteous and glorious Kingdome and Government, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. 1 - 7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 16 - 19. &amp; 66. 22. &amp; 11. &amp; 32. 1 - 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. <hi>And the Lord ſhall be one, and his name one throughout all the earth,</hi> Zach. 14. 9. <hi>And the knowledge of the Lord ſhall cover the earth, as the waters cover the Sea,</hi> Hab. 2. 14. And there ſhall be great and wonderful Converſions, and daily flocking in with joy, as Doves to their windows, to the Name of the Lord in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of the Nations of them that are ſaved from the former deſolating Judgements and Conſumptions, among which alſo the natural <hi>Iſraelites</hi> then ſurviving ſhall be chief, to fill the face of the world with fruit againe, and to be Subjects of this glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (for all the children of the firſt Reſurrection of Jews and Gentiles ſhall be Reigners) And to walk in the light of the new Jeruſalem, <hi>They ſhall flow together to the name of the Lord in Sion,</hi> Iſa. 2. Mich. 4. Iſa. 9. 4, 5, 6, &amp; 24. 13, 14. &amp; 66. 19. &amp;c. Zach. 2. 11. &amp; 8. 22. &amp; 16. Rev. 21. 24. Pſal. 102. and though there ſhall bee no more Death, nor fruits of Sin in the New Jeruſalem, or upon the Children of the Reſurrection, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. 3, 4. no nor Night, nor need of the Sun or M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on to that City, when yet the glory and brightneſs of them (in that reſtitution of all things) ſhall be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven fold to what it is, and ſo uſeful in and so all the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the ſubjects of this glorious Kingdome, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. 26. &amp; 60. 19, &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 22, 23, 25. Neither ſhall there be any more wars, or tumults among the Nations one againſt another in the time of that glorious Kingdom, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. nor ſhall there be that heavie Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of corruption remaining on the Creature, or enmity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them that is now, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 19. 25. <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 20, 21. and ſo none of thoſe poyſonous Infections, or unnatural Diſeaſes, or untimely Deaths, that now are common to man, ſhall be then common to any, or accidentally, or caſually befall them; yet as there ſhall be extraordinary and immediate Judgements from God then falling on thoſe Nations, Families, and Perſons that will not voluntarily ſerve under this Government, and come up to worſhip
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32511:16"/>
the Name of the Lord in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> even to the cutting them off, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 12. <hi>Zach.</hi> 14. 16 - 19. even ſo there may, yea there muſt needs bee ſome remainders of mortality, and the Natural death generally on the people, the Subjects of this glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the people that ſhall then be left of the Nations, and that ſhall then be created, or born to praiſe the Lord, who yet have not paſſed through that change. According to Gods appointment, <hi>All must once dye,</hi> amongſt which ſome will bee found even then dying in their ſins, not coming up to worſhip the Lord, and his Name in <hi>Sion</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (in Chriſt, and the children of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) as proclaimed and ſhining forth from that great City, that ſhal be the glory of all Lands; and others dying in the Lord (as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 16, 17 - 20. of which happily ſome may immediately be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and faſhioned into the likeneſſe of his glorious Body; but ſome even of them ſhall ſtay, or reſt in death until that great and general Reſurrection that ſhall be after the finiſhing of that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, for in that Reſurrection it is evidently ſignified, that there ſhall be ſome found written in the Book of Life, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 12 - 15. and they muſt needs be of them that lived, and dyed in the time of that thouſand years, or were immediately changed in the finiſhing of the ſame; for all that ſlept in Chriſt before that day of Chriſts appearing in his glory, and the ſurvivers of that body then were brought together with him, to the inheriting &amp; reigning in that glorious Kingdome. <hi>Then after that cometh the end, when he ſhall have delivered up the Kingdome to God, even the Father, when he ſhall have put down all rule, and all authority, and power, for be muſt reign in this</hi> Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torial, and Davidical Kingdom, <hi>till he have put all his enemies under his feet, the laſt enemy that ſhall be deſtroyed is Death,</hi> which though perfectly deſtroyed in the children of the firſt Reſurrection, in the beginning of that glorious day, even immediately on his deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or coming down from Heaven, yet not wholly deſtroyed from being an enemy, while it holds the wicked from their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting puniſhment, and vengeance, in which God ſhall be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and the righteous ſhall glory for ever; and while alſo it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains ſome of thoſe worſhippers of him, whoſe names (as ſuch) are written in the Book of Life from the foundation of the world, even ſuch of them as dyed in that time of his reign on the earth, from the poſſeſſion of their utmoſt happineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:32511:16"/>Therefore in the concluſion of that day of his Reign, or of that manner of Adminiſtration of the Kingdome (for the Kingdome, and the glory of it is everlaſting, and never ſhall have end) all the reſt of the dead, ſmall and great ſhall be raiſed by him out of their Graves, and from the diſappearing ſtate of Death, and ſhall appear before his Judgement Seat. This is the ſecond, and laſt Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>So that there ſhall be a general Reſurrection of the juſt, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, which in both parts our Saviour diſtinguiſheth from that firſt fruites of quickning of the ſpirit, from that death in ſins and treſpaſſes, which is now effected by the light and power of the Goſpel in them that in hearing hear, of which work of Spiritual quickning now, having ſpoken in <hi>Job.</hi> 5. 25. hee adds <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. <hi>Marvel not at this</hi> (as who ſhould ſay, that which I ſhall now tell you of is not only another, but a greater work, and ſo a greater and more glorious evidence of the vertue and power of the voyce of the Son of Man) <hi>for the hour is coming</hi> (he ſaith not and now is, as of the former work, <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. in which leaving out that Clauſe here, having added it to the former, he fully ſignifies that it is not now; and yet here he ſpeaks of the whole and general Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Dead in both the parts, firſt and ſecond) in which, <hi>all that are in the Graves</hi> (or in the diſappearing ſtate of death) <hi>ſhall hear the voyce of the Son of Man</hi> (in an immediate, wonderful, and mighty putting forth of it) <hi>and ſhall come forth, they that have done good, to the reſurrection of life, and they that have done evil, to the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of this Reſurrection in both parts (and at both times as in the other Scriptures) Chriſt is in the Name of the Father the only foundation, and Author, even as the Son of Man; for had he not dyed, roſe, and revived for them all, and therein by himſelf pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our ſin: in which we had all ſinned, and were become ſinful, and dead, he could not have been our Lord, and Judge, according to the rule of the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 22 - 27. nor could any have been raiſed from the firſt Death, and brought before his Judgement Seat by him, if he had not by the grace of God taſted Death for them. Therefore with reſpect to that general Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction at the laſt Day, confeſſed by <hi>Martha,</hi> Joh. 11. our Saviour ſaith, <hi>I am the reſurrection,</hi> verſ. 25. The Foundation and Author of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32511:17"/>
that general Reſurrection in the laſt day, both of juſt and unjuſt; and ſo he is the life from the dead, that eternal life which was with the Father for men, and is now manifeſted, that it may bee known and enjoyed; he is the Author, Fountain, and in a ſence, the matter of it, as delivered to Death for our offences, and raiſed again for our Juſtification; therefore, <hi>whoſoever beleeveth in him, though he were dead,</hi> yea though they dye in common with others, <hi>yet ſhall he live, and he that liveth and beleeveth on him ſhall never dye,</hi> (as before ſaid, in the full and proper ſence of the word) the firſt Death being aboliſhed, and they by him delivered from that wrath, which in reſpect of the execution of it, is yet to come on them that know not God, nor obey to his Goſpel; they are not cut off from him, or from their hope in death, as others are, yea he being the Reſurrection, they his peculiar Treaſure, muſt needs have the firſtneſſe, and bleſſedneſs of that, yea they in having him by faith in his name (as <hi>Joh. 1. 12. Epheſ. 3. 17. 1 Joh.</hi> 5. 10-12, 13.) have part in the firſt reſurrection in the knowledge, faith, and hope of it in him; and the righteouſneſſe of God, and our Saviour, is ingaged for the making them partakers of it actually in themſelves, in the accompliſhing it upon them together in his time, for which they are all waiters till that Perſonal appearance of the Lord in his glory, which hee now being raiſed from the dead actually poſſeſſeth, and holdeth for them in Heaven with the Father, and ſo is to, and in them, by faith, the hope of it; which hope they having in him, it makes them confident, and patient in waiting for the enjoyment of it, <hi>Rom. 8. 23, 24, 25. 2 Cor.</hi> 4, 13. &amp; 5. 1. 6, 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 19, 20.</p>
            <p>So that they periſh not, nor are at all cut off from their bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by death, but from henceforth more bleſſed, and ſealed up to the full enjoyment of that bleſſedneſſe, and holineſſe with him for ever, even the periect bloſting our, and delivering them from all their tranſgreſſions, and the fruits of them, and the making them perfectly like him in holineſſe, and glory in ſoul and body for ever, in that time and ſtate of the firſt reſurrection, in which they ſhall be perfectly delivered from the firſt Death, to the full enjoyment and poſſeſſion of everlaſting life; in the knowledge, faith, and hope of which, their ſpirits now are made alive, or in part quickned from that Death in ſins and treſpaſſes (which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:32511:17"/>
but a part of that firſt Death that paſſed on all men at firſt by Sin, while yet their bodies are dead becauſe of ſin, which alſo in that day of Chriſt ſhall be raiſed up together by him, and the ſecond Death ſhall have no power on them; his teſtimony having been beleeved by them in their day, and through it they being found in him, ſhall not be found naked to the ſecond Death, and if not to that, then to no following death or miſery for ever; for we read, or hear of no third Death, unleſs in ſome unlearned diſtinctions, not found or known in the Scriptures, which diſtinctions doe ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Natural and Bodily death, in which it is appointed to men once to dye, to be the ſecond Death, whereas indeed it is but the finiſhing of the firſt Death on the Body, or its full ſeizure on it, and that which the Holy Ghoſt calls the Second Death, they call the Third; in which rendering the Natural Death of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be the Second Death. They intimately deny the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the body from that Death; for Scripture informeth us, that <hi>out of the Second Death there is no reſurrection or redemption,</hi> and doe therein render that which they call the third Death, to have no terrour, torment, or puniſhment in it to be felt, and ſuſtained by the body (for that can be capable of no ſuch thing if it never be raiſed) but at moſt by the Spirit only, without the Body, in which the evil deeds were done; and ſo this diſtinction renders that which Scripture knows by no other name but <hi>The Second Death</hi> (though by them called the Third) to be much eaſier than the Firſt, for that did ſeize, not on the ſpirit or ſoul only, but on the body alſo. But the Scripture every where repreſents it infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſe, and more dreadful in every conſideration, and to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for ever in ſoul and body together, when the body ſhall bee raiſed from the firſt death in that reſurrection of Damnation, in which it ſhall be rendered capable of ſuffering everlaſting and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable vengeance and torment, according to the infinite grace now abuſed by them, for according to his fear, or grace, and name in Chriſt, that he might be feared by men now, ſuch his wrath and terrour then againſt his enemies, <hi>Pſal. 90. 11. 2 Cor. 5. 10, 11. 14, 15. 20, 21. Heb.</hi> 2. 1-4. and who then can comprehend the greatneſs and power of it, when though they ſhall ſuffer the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt horrour, anguiſh, and torment that an utter ſeparation from God, and wrath deſerved, by treading under foot his Son, cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32511:18"/>
his Bloud an unholy thing, and in all this, offering deſpite to his Spirit, being poured out to the utmoſt, may occaſion to them, yet nothing ſhall make either ſoul or body ceaſe to be, or be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated any more as they were in the firſt Death, that there ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be any releaſe, abatement, or intermiſſion in the whole, or in part, of that weeping, wayling, and gnaſhing of teeth world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end; yea their worm dyeth not, and their fire is not quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor is there any darkneſs, or ſhadow of death, in which the workers of iniquity may hide themſelves. O then it will appear, that <hi>Bleſſed are all they that truſt in him;</hi> yea therefore from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord,</hi> they having part in the firſt Reſurrection, this ſecond Death ſhall have no power on them.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, they that in death, which terminates the gathering time and ſpace of repentance, are found out of the Lord, dying in their ſins, they are then, and thence for ever blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the Book of Life, cut off from all hopes of ever at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, or having part in the firſt Reſurrection; though they ſhall be all of them raiſed, and made alive from the firſt death, and then, and therein brought to the clear ſight, and acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the truth of the grace of God in the Lordſhip of Chriſt, through his death, ſometimes, and while it was due time bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Salvation to them; that which here they wilfully rejected when light came to them, and which if it had been now received in its own light and power bringing Salvation, would have been to their everlaſting comfort, in the quickning them to a new and living hope through the reſurrection of Chriſt; they ſhall then confeſs to the glory of God, and clearing his Juſtice, in judging them for ever according to the rule of his Goſpel to a ſecond and never dying death, infinitely worſe than the firſt, and in ſealing them up in Priſon from the time of their filling up the meaſure of their ſin of that nature, which is at the utmoſt, at the time of the end of their Natural life, when he hath done ſtriving with them, and waiting to be gracious, I ſay, in his ſealing them up in priſon from ſuch time to that dreadful Judgement, <hi>Iſa. 45. 23. Phil. 2. 10, 11. Rom.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
            <p>From which time they are ſhut up under the ſentence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of that ſecond Death, and ſo in reſpect of their ſtate
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32511:18"/>
and condition, are from thence Trees twice dead, pluckt up by the roots, though the wrath, in reſpect of the full and moſt dreadful execution of it, on ſoul and body for ever, is yet to come, ſo that in death they periſh for ever from the preſence of the Lord, and from his favour, in which is life; the wicked is driven away in his wickedneſs, but the righteous hath hope in his death.</p>
            <p>So then, they that are fallen aſleep in Chriſt are not periſhed, or cut off for their parts, no not from their union with Chriſt, by vertue of which, even their bodies that ſleep in the duſt ſhall bee firſt raiſed even to the reſurrection of life, yea they are from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth and more then ever bleſſed, the day of their death infinitely better to them, than the day that they were born. We come next to conſider, in what ſence ſuch perſons may be ſaid to periſh, and when they ſo doe; and this we ſhall finde explicated to us in the other expreſſions of this chaſtiſement in this verſe, as compared with other Scriptures, they are ſaid to periſh from the earth, to ceaſe, and fail from among men that yet ſurvive, when by Death they are taken away from them, they having no more a portion in any thing done under the Sun, nor capacity of being helpful to the ſurvivers in any knowledge, wiſdome, or work, for in death there is no remembrance or commemoration of him among the ſurvivers; in the Grave who ſhall give him thanks, or praiſe him to others, yet living, or ſhew forth their hoping in his truth; <hi>The living, the living he ſhall praiſe thee</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hezekiah) as I doe this day, the Fathers to the Children ſhall make known thy truth;</hi> which expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates in what ſence the dead praiſe him not, nor hope for his truth, that is, they celebrate not his praiſes among the ſurvivors, nor are capable of exerciſing or ſhewing forth their hoping in his truth to them-ward, or among them, they cannot make known his truth to them, and ſo not praiſe him as he did then, the Fathers to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>Eccl. 9. 10. Pſa. 6. 5. Iſa.</hi> 38. 18, 19. for otherwiſe in reſpect of themſelves, and to Godward, the dead in Chriſt even in theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects doe live, they retain their hope in death, and joy in it; yea they enter into a more full and peaceable enjoyment of it in ſpirit, their ſpirits are made perfect, each one walking in his upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and are ſtill confidently expecting, longing, and waiting for that day of full Redemption, even the redemption of their body, and the judging and revenging their ſufferings and wrongs on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32511:19"/>
them that dwell on the earth, crying, <hi>Lord, how long,</hi> Prov. 14. 32. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 23. Revel. 6. 9, 10, 11. They are with Chriſt, which to them is farre better, as is ſhewed before; but they are dead to us, and can no longer in their perſons be profitable to us, which made the Apoſtles and Prophets in their longing deſire of the good of all, and for the furtherance of the Goſpel among men, and that the truth of it might remain with thoſe that had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, ſo much deſire to abide with them, even to abide in the fleſh in this body, though ſo much to their own diſadvantage, preferring others good before their own; in death they periſh, ceaſe, and depart from us, and are out of capacity of being helpful to us.</p>
            <p>And yet further, Theſe Scriptures; <hi>The Righteous periſheth, the good man is periſhed out of the Earth,</hi> and ſo the cauſe of grief here la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, is not verified ſimply in the taking away one, or diverſe of the Righteous by death; but when alſo they are taken away as ſuch a time, and in ſuch manner, as that there is none of like faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to God, and kindneſſe to men left in the place, or places where they lived, to ſurvive them, or at leaſt none in their room, or ſtead: But that if one or more of them be taken away, there is ſo many the leſſe of that Generation, or Righteous Nation that keepeth the Truth, left in the midſt of the crooked, and perverſe Nation, to ſhine as lights in the world: Moſt ſadly and fully is it verified, when there is none left in the place, or places, whence they are taken; and thus is this matter of lamentation explicated in the expreſſions of it in other Scriptures, as <hi>Pſal,</hi> 12. 1. <hi>Help Lord, for the godly man ceaſeth, the faithful fail from among the children of men;</hi> ſo <hi>Micah</hi> 7. 1, 2. <hi>Woe is mee, for I am as when they have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the Summer fruits, as the Grape gleanings of the Vintage, no cluſter, &amp;c. The good man is periſhed out of the Earth, and there is none up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right among men:</hi> Oh that the matter of this ſad complaint were not too ſadly verified amongſt us, and in this place at this time. Theſe things being thus opened, wee ſhall briefly demonſtrate and explicate the poſition. That the periſhing of the Righteous, the taking away of men of kindneſſe, and godlineſſe, is a ſad cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to the ſurvivers, which God would have laid to heart by them. For proof of this</p>
            <p>There needs no more, than the Scriptures already cited, where
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:32511:19"/>
we ſee that the ſervants of God take it as a heavy chaſtiſement, wo and miſery to themſelves, the taking away of ſuch faithful labourers, and fellow-helpers with them, as were inſtruments of drawing others in, and gathering them together in cluſters, to the acknowledgement, and ſeeking of the name of God in Chriſt; and ſtrivers together with them, for the faith of the Goſpel, and ſo helpers of their faith, and joy. So the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Philippians</hi> concerning <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> (his brother and compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in labours, and fellow-ſouldier; and their meſſenger) That hee had been ſick, nigh unto death, ſaith, that God had mercy on him, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in reſtoring the ſaid <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> again, leſt hee ſhould have ſorrow upon ſorrow, where he plainly ſignifies, that it would have been a very great chaſtiſement, and occaſion of grief and ſorrow to him; if <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> had then been taken away. And how much more heavy is the correction, or judgement, to thoſe ſocieties, or companies of people to whom they were more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly meſſengers, and ſet as guides to go before them in the word of the Lord; and ſo to the people generally among whom they lived. It is mentioned as a heavy judgement on the Nation, and people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> wee ſee not our ſignes, there is no more any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, neither is there among us any that knoweth, how long, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 74. 9. and ſo threatned, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. <hi>That he would lay the land moſt deſolate,</hi> even <hi>the Mountains of</hi> Iſrael, ſo as when it ſhould come to paſſe, <hi>they ſhould know that a Prophet had been among them</hi> (verſes 28, 29, 33.) Intimating, they ſhould then know, by their being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of him, and ſo know what their mercy was they ſleighted, by the want of it. And truly it muſt needs bee a heavy correction and judgement to that place, or people, from amongſt whom the Righteous ſo periſh, or f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> from the earth, and from among the children of men. For theſe reaſons,</p>
            <p>1 They are ſet in the world, and preſerved in it, and from the evil of it while they are continued in it, for the good of the world, even of all men among whom they live, yea their Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors to be as Inſtruments in Gods hand, for the opening their eyes, and turning them from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan to God; <hi>They are the ſalt of the earth, the light of the world, a choſen Generation, that they ſhould ſhew forth the praiſes of him that hath called them out of darkneſſe into his marvellous light, and ſhine as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32511:20"/>
lights in the world, by holding forth the word of life in word and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,</hi> Joh. 17. 15-18. 23. Acts 26. 17, 18. Matth. 5. 13-16. 1 Pet. 2. 9, 10, &amp;c. Phil. 2. 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. Yea,</p>
            <p>2 Their being ſo preſerved in the world, not taken out of it, that is, not ſo taken out, but that there may bee a Generation of them continued ſucceſſively, and they in their ſeveral Ages preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and kept from the evil of the world to the end fore-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it is one of the maine things for which Jeſus Chriſt appears in the preſence of God, making interceſſion for the good of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors; therefore while any of them are graciouſly preſerved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong any people, it is an evidence of the powerful mediation of Chriſt (whom the Father hears in all his Petitions) yet continued and graciouſly exerciſed for that people, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 15-23. Whence the Apoſtle exhorts, not to receive this grace of God in vain, becauſe God ſaith, <hi>In an accepted time I have heard thee,</hi> that is, Chriſt making interceſſion for them, <hi>in a day of ſalvation I have helped thee:</hi> which he doth, in helping, ſupporting, and preſerving his Servants, to hold forth the Word of Life among others in word and converſation; <hi>Behold, this is the accepted time, this is the day of Salvation,</hi> namely, while they the Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, were inſtructing, exhorting, beſeeching, reproving, &amp;c. while their mouth was open, their heart enlarged, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 1, 2, 11. with Chap. 5. 20.</p>
            <p>Theſe conſiderations demonſtrate, the Righteous periſhing and failing from among a people, to bee a heavy correction and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, even of this nature.</p>
            <p>1 Such as in which God taketh, or is taking away their Candleſtick out of his place, where he had ſet and preſerved it to give light to others, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. Yea</p>
            <p>2 Such as in which the good man of the houſe appears as riſen, or riſing up out of his place of mercy, and forbearance, in which hee hath been long holding open the door of life; now to ſhut it againſt ſuch a people for ever, if they ſpeedily repent not. Such it is, as in which there is an appearance of the end, or nigh approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the end of his time, in which hee is pleading with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſparing, or letting the fruitleſſe Fig-tree alone, that hee may yet digge about it, and dung it; according to that, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 6, 7, 8, 9. like that, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. A judgement of a far higher nature,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:32511:20"/>
than a famine of Bread, <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 11, 12. Theſe are ſuch provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, as in which in ſome meaſure God is declaring men repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſilver, on whom the bellows is burnt, the lead conſumed, the founder melteth in vain, and therefore fit to bee left as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, and no more pains to be taken with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> The Poſition thus opened, let it admoniſh us to conſider and lay to heart even this ſad providence before it be too late, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Decree bring forth, and we be as chaffe that paſſeth, &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Jeremy</hi> in his <hi>Lamentation,</hi> on ſuch an occaſion, teacheth us to make this uſe of ſuch Providences, <hi>viz. To ſearch and try our waies, and turn to the Lord,</hi> Lam. 3. 39, 40. If when his hand is lifted up, and his Judgements begin ſadly to be powred out upon us, we yet learn righteouſneſs, he will yet bee gracious, and in the midſt of wrath remember mercy; let us then be ſo wiſe as to hear the Rod, and who hath apponted it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> conſider the meaning of the Voyce; and that we may underſtand it, let us conſult with the Scriptures, what manner of iniquities are uſually puniſhed with ſuch Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>We ſhall finde one great Head of Iniquity that is found in many Branches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in divers branches of it, to have been puniſhed with ſuch Judgements, is, <hi>The not diſcerning the Lords Body; for this cauſe,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 30. <hi>not only many are weak, and ſickly, but alſo many ſleep;</hi> which though a mercy to them that ſleep in Jeſus, to be ſo taken away from the evil, yet a Judgement to the ſurvivers procured to themſelves, by their not diſcerning the Lords Body.</p>
            <p>The Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Body is firſt and primely his Perſonal Body, and of that he was ſpeaking immediately before, <hi>ver.</hi> 27. yea the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of that as broken for us, and the infinite grace and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the ſufferings ſuſtained therein, is the ſubject matter of his Diſcourſe there.</p>
            <p>The Lords Body in a ſecondary ſence is, his Myſtical Body, his Church, thoſe that through the taſtes of his graciouſneſs are built upon him, in whom the poor and rich, bond and free, Brother of high degree, and of low, do meet together, they being all in coming to him through the taſtes of his grace, and ſo in being baptized into him, baptized into one Body, and made to drink into one ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:32511:21"/>Now that not diſcerning, perceiving, conſidering, knowing, or owning the Lords Body, that the Holy Ghoſt charges upon men as their ſin, and God judges them for, is not ſuch weakneſs, or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as is of neceſſity through natural frailty, or for want of means and diſcoveries vouchſafed, but a wilful and rebellious, not knowing, diſcerning, or taking notice of it, in the evidence and demonſtration of the Spirit in the teſtimony of Jeſus, ſetting it before them, and therein opening the eyes, and lifting up the yoke of Natural thraldome, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11. <hi>This is the condemnation, that when light comes, men love darkneſs rather, becauſe their deeds are evil, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the light,</hi> Joh. 3. 19. And ſo when the righteous, the true worſhippers of God in Chriſt, that are ſet as Lights in the world, holding forth the word of Life in the demonſtration of the Spirit, and with power are lifting up the Son of Man in what hee hath done, and is become for ſinners; and the infinite vertue and grace of his Perſonal ſufferings, and Sacrifice, and therein ſhewing forth his vertues and praiſes, and ſo in both preaching not themſelves, but Jeſus Chriſt the Lord, and rendring themſelves ſervants to all for his ſake, beſeeching, alluring, and drawing them in the light and power of his Spirit with them (as <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11. <hi>Zach.</hi> 7. 9 - 12, 13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 14 - 20. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 12 - 16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9 - 13, &amp;c.) even to the moſt High to conſider the Lords Body, and in the grace and power of its vertue and demonſtrations to bee reconciled to God; yet none at all will exalt him, but are bent to back-ſlidings, when ſo called, allured, drawn, and wrought upon; they will not know, nor regard the Work of the Lord, or the operation of his hands, but deſpiſe both him and them for his ſake, neglecting ſo great Salvation.</p>
            <p>This iniquity is found in many Branches, as we ſhall ſee in this, and the other Scriptures, where theſe Judgements are bewayled, and the reaſon of them given; As,</p>
            <p>1 When by the righteous and merciful men, the large extent of the infinite grace and vertue of the Lords Death is ſo commended, and lifted up, that the Lords Houſe, his Temple, where he may bee worſhipped, and place of entertainment in his Son, and with them that call upon him in truth, is preſented as a houſe of Prayer for all people, where a rich Feaſt, and Treaſury of all things pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to life and godlineſs is prepared, and ſet on the Table for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32511:21"/>
them all, that all through his grace might come in thither, and eate of his Bread, and drink of the Wine that hee hath mingled, and that whoſoever comes by him in the light and power of his drawings, while his grace is bringing Salvation to them, as it doth to all in due time, might be accepted; and therefore graciouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting them all, as in the Chapters before the text, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 1 - 7. &amp; 56. 7, 8. with <hi>Prov.</hi> 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1 - 8. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 14, 15, 16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 14, 15 - 19, 20, 21. &amp; 6. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>Yet men not only ſet light by it, neglect ſo great Salvation, make excuſes, and will not come, but alſo wilfully cloſe their eyes, and harden their hearts againſt this grace of God that brings Salvation to all men; and alſo like the Beaſts of the Field come to devour, forbidding the plaine and faithful preaching of the Goſpel of Chriſt to the world, that through him they might bee ſaved. In which they pleaſe not God, and are contrary to the good of all men, and perſiſting in this wilful oppoſition of the grace of God in the Lords Death to all men, they fill up the meaſure of their ſin, till wrath come upon them to the utmoſt, 1 <hi>Theſſ. 2. 15, 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this way of iniquity are found chiefly, and as Ring-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the Generality of the Watch-men, the Maſters, Teachers, and builders that are approved by, and of high account with men, they come chiefly under this charge in the Chapter before the text, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 9, 10, &amp;c. His Watch-men, (the Watchmen of their owne ſetting up and approving) are blinde, and ignorant, not having learned truth as in Jeſus, but profeſſing to be wiſe in Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence falſly ſo called, and thinking thereby to comprehend the things of God in Chriſt, have erred from the faith, and turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide to vaine jangling, the generality of them have in all Ages re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, and ſet at nought that Stone which God hath made, the foundation and head of the corner, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. 22. <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 42. with Chap. 22. 1 - 15. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 10. 14 - 15, &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 11, 12. <hi>Job.</hi> 7. 48, 49. And where any of them doe ſee any truth in that Doctrine, that exalts, or lifts up the Son of Man, and Gods glory in him, yet they are dumb, and will not confeſs it, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. 42, 43. <hi>Among the chief Rulers alſo many beleeved on him, but becauſe of the Phariſees they did not confeſs him, leaſt they ſhould bee put out of the Sinagogue, for they loved the praiſe of men more then the praiſe of God;</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:32511:22"/>
yea they generally love to flumber, are loath to be ſtirred up, and awakened, to conſider and ſet their hearts to that which might bee for their owne and others good, but lying down to ſleep, doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and ſtop their ears againſt that knowledge of him that comes to awaken them to righteouſneſs, and diſcovers the falſeneſs and vanity of their Dreams. See further what follows of them, in that <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. with 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 - 5.</p>
            <p>2 Another ſort there are, that doe not ſo much, or directly ſet themſelves to oppoſe the Doctrine of the Grace of God in Chriſt, or the preaching thereof, yet will not diligently mind or conſider it, or the weight, importance, tendency, and inſtructions of it, but doe inwardly ſhun the light and power of it, and harden their hearts againſt the evidence and demonſtration of the Spirit in it, becauſe it diſcovers and reproves their deeds as evil, not ſuffering grace to make them willing in the day of his Power, ſo to receive the love of the Truth as that they might be ſaved by it, doe wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reject, and harden their hearts againſt the reproofs of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Lords Voyce crying unto them, diſcovering, and reproving their Covetouſneſs, Oppreſſion, In-juſtice, Violence, leaſt they ſhould be converted and healed by it. And in this are found chiefly the generality of the rich men, and Rulers of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; ſee at large <hi>Micha</hi> 6. declaring the procuring cauſe of that Judgement, of the good man periſhing out of the earth, ſuch they were, as that the good man being periſhed, or taken away from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, the beſt of them was a Bryar, and the moſt upright as a Thorn-hedge, ſee <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. 3. 4, 5. yea in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> time, many of them did ſhew much love and reſpect to the Prophet while hee was among them, and he was to them as a pleaſant Song, yet they would not regard his words to doe them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to ſuffer their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving operation in them, for their heart went after their covetouſnes, and that is there given as the reaſon of the Judgement threatned, in which they ſhould know, that a Prophet had been among them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 30 - 33.</p>
            <p>3 Others there are, that through the knowledge of God in Chriſt have made ſome eſcape from them that live in errour, and from the pollutions that are in the world through Luſt, and ſome of them have ſtood againſt many ſtrong temptations, and have tried thoſe that ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not, and found them
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32511:22"/>
Lyars, and yet after all this, <hi>turn again with the Dogge to his vomit, and with the Sow to her wallowing in the mire,</hi> leaving their firſt love to that perſon, and to the excellent knowledge of him. Some with a more high hand then others, turn from the holy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after knowledge of the truth received, and turning away their ears from the truth, are turned aſide to Fables, even to ſuch damnable Hereſies, as in which privily under pretence of magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, the Lord that bought them is denied by them; others cleaving to, and embracing this preſent world, not continuing in, but forſaking the Apoſtles Doctrine, and Fellowſhip, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, or conſidering, and remembring the excellency, grace, and vertue of the Lords Body that was broken for us; and for ſuch like iniquity God threatens the removing of their Candleſtick, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 1 - 5.</p>
            <p>Now if yet we would judge our ſelves, we ſhould not be further judged of the Lord, if when his hand is lifted up even to deſtroy, and make an utter deſolation, yet if any take notice of it, and ſay; <hi>I have ſinned, and perverted that which was right, and it profited mee not;</hi> then he is gracious, and ſaith, <hi>Deliver him from going down to the pit, for I have found a ranſome; If we confeſs our ſins, he is faithful and juſt to forgive us our ſins, and the bloud of Jeſus cleanſeth us from all ſin, but he that hideth his ſin ſhall not proſper;</hi> hee that being often repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved hardneth his neck, ſhall ſuddenly fall, and that without remedy; and this leads us to the next Branch of inſtruction, namely,</p>
            <p>2 That when God ſo ſtrikes, and yet none lay to heart, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it; its an evidence of great hardneſſe, and wilful blindneſſe in ſuch a people, and a ſign and fore-runner of greater judgements. The truth of this is evidenced in the fore-mentioned Scriptures, yet for farther, and more particular demonſtration of it. See alſo, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 9. Oh Lord! when thine hand is lifted up, they will not ſee it, but they ſhall ſee, and be aſhamed, &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. When God hath threatned, and begun to make deſolations (as <hi>chap.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Then he ſaith, <hi>Run to and fro through the ſtreets and broad places, And ſee now if yee can finde a man, if there be any that executeth judgement, that ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the truth, and I will pardon it.</hi> And though they ſay, <hi>The Lord li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth,</hi> and ſwear by his Name, ſurely they ſwear falſly; <hi>O Lord, are not thine eyes upon the truth? thou hast ſtricken them, but they have not grieved; thou haſt conſumed them, but they have refuſed to receive
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:32511:23"/>
correction, they have made their faces harder than a rock, they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to return;</hi> and in this alſo the poor and rich did agree to break the yoke, and burſt the bands, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Therefore a Lion out of the Forreſt ſhall ſlay them;</hi> A Wolf of the Evenings, that comes privily to devour, like that ſpirit of Antichriſt, and miniſters of Satan, Propheſied of to abound in the laſt days, that come with all deceiveableneſs of unrighteouſneſs in them that periſh, privily bringing in damnable Hereſies, denying the Lord that bought them, ſuch an enemy ſhall ſpoyl and deſtroy them; <hi>God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions</hi> (by giving permiſſive commiſſion to Satan, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the caſe of <hi>Ahah,</hi> 1 King. 22. 19,—22.) <hi>that they ſhould beleeve a lye, that they all might bee damned, who beleeved not the truth, but bad pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe;</hi> Surely his ſoul ſhall be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this. See alſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78, 64, 65, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What then ſhall wee ſay, when in ſtead of laying it to heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and conſidering it, and being grieved, many rejoyce, and ſport themſelves at ſuch judgements, as <hi>Micah</hi> 7. 8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 3, 4. imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they ſhall now have their deſire, and that the Righteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken away, their name, even the good name of God that was upon them, ſhall periſh, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. 5, 6, 7. and therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage themſelves in their evil wayes, doctrines, and practiſes, faithful reprovers, that were a terrour to them, being ceaſed from them; now they ſay (as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.) <hi>our tongues are our own, who is Lord over us.</hi> And now a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men delivered to do ſuch abominations, they ſpeak vanity, every one with his neighbour, with a flattering lip, and double heart, thinking to prevail with their lip, or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; now to root out the lip of knowledge, encouraging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as if the foundations of the righteous were deſtroyed, and therefore reproachfully ſaying to the poor, that hath no helper but God, and yet puts his truſt in him, where is now thy God, thy hope, thy confidence—what can the righteous do? <hi>Mic.</hi> 7. 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11. But our God, who is our rock, and foundation is in his holy Temple, in his Son our very preſent help, and ſtrong Tower of defence to ſave us, The Lords throne is in Heaven, from whence his eyes behold, his eye lids trye the children of men, hee is a God, by whom actions are weighed in an even ballance, and though hee do not ſpeedily execute judgement againſt evil works, becauſe hee delights in mercy, and would not that any
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32511:23"/>
ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance, ſuch his gracious affection towards ſinners, even rebellious ones in this day of his grace, and patience, yet all theſe things are laid up in ſtore with him, ſealed up among his treaſures, and ſhall be brought forth, when every ſecret thing ſhall bee brought to light, and God ſhall manifeſt the counſels of the heart, then no more patience, or forbearance to bee exerciſed towards rebels; the Lord ſhall laugh then at their calamity, and mock when their fear commeth; yea, the Lord himſelf ſhall come, and ten thouſands of his Saints, to execute judgement upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly amongſt them, of all their ungodly deeds, which they have ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt him, Then the Lord ſhall cut off all flattering lips, and the tongue that ſpeaketh proud things, &amp;c. for to him belongeth vengeance; <hi>their foot ſhall ſlide in due time, &amp;c. Deut.</hi> 32. 34, 35, &amp;c. <hi>Jude</hi> 14, 15. In the mean time therefore let us look to him for counſel, and ſee what uſe hee inſtructs us to make of this conſideration, when we ſhall ſee the daies ſo evil, and iniquity thus abounding, and evil men, and deceivers waxing worſe and worſe, by every warning and judgement. Truly then</p>
            <p>1 Let them alone, withdraw from them, reprove not a ſcorner, leſt hee hate thee; for hee that reproveth a ſcorner, getteth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhame, he that rebuketh a wicked man, getteth himſelf a blot, though ſtill as grace inſtructs, wee may yet mourn in ſecret for their pride, as <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. 17. And not bee haſty in deſiring the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful day; but let our prayer bee for them, if yet there may bee hope, even when God appears to bee riſing up, as one that will no more be intreated; See <hi>Jer.</hi> 14, &amp; 15.</p>
            <p>2 If there be any that will hear, be diligent, and earneſt in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, in inſtructing, and admoniſhing them, while it is to day, not to harden their hearts; rebuke a wife man, and hee will love thee, and be yet wiſer, and with meekneſſe inſtruct them that ignorantly oppoſe themſelves, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>3 And let us together be admoniſhed 1 In the way of his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to wait for the Lord, quietly to bear his indignation, becauſe we have ſinned, and reverently liſtening to him, and ſtanding in awe before him under ſuch teſtimonies of diſpleaſure, knowing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32511:24"/>
that he is righteous and faithful, as well as infinite in wiſdome, and power, as hee hath manifeſted himſelf in that faithful witneſſe, ſetled for ever in Heaven, and in due time hee will bring us forth, and wee ſhall behold his righteouſneſſe: Then ſhe that is mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhall bee aſhamed, <hi>Micah</hi> 7. 6. 10. And fret not our ſelves becauſe of evil doers, wait patiently on the Lord, commit our way to him, and hee ſhall bring it to paſſe; deſpiſe not his chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, neither faint when rebuked of him, ſeeing it is the Lord; The helpers taken from us were no otherwiſe helpers, but in the Lord, and hee hath not taken himſelf from us in whom is our help. 2 When wee ſee how the reproaches, and blaſphemies of men are increaſed againſt him, and do ſet themſelves againſt the heavena; let the conſideration of it, make us more willing to bear them, ſeeing they are the reproaches of them, that reproach him, that fall on us, and commit vengeance to him. 3 Bee wee ſtirred up to cry mightily to God for help, <hi>Help Lord, for the godly man ceaſeth, the faithful fail from among the children of men;</hi> they ſpeak vanity every one with his neighbour, with a flattering lip, and double heart do they ſpeak; cry therefore with more earneſtneſſe to God in Chriſt. 1 For pardon of our iniquities, and healing of our diſtempers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. 4, 5, and 38. 12,—16, 17,—19. 2 For wiſdome in the knowledge of him, and thoſe great things of his Law, that may guide us in a plain path, becauſe of our enemies that watch for our halting, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 8—11, &amp;c. And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe alſo, 4 Let us redeem the preſent time yet left us, and bee admoniſhed by his judgements to awake to righteouſneſſe, and not ſin againſt him; for it is a ſhame for us that wee are yet found ſo much without the knowledge of him; what, <hi>the ſummer paſt, the harveſt ended, and yet wee not ſaved?</hi> Jer. 8. 20. Oh that at leaſt in this day, before it bee wholly paſt, wee did wiſely conſider our latter end; yea, the rather becauſe the dayes are evil, redeem the time, and be not unwiſe, but underſtanding what the will of the Lord is; and to that purpoſe, take heed to our ſelves leſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> any time our hearts be overcharged, with ſurfetting and drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſſe, or cares of this life, and ſo the day of death, and of judgement come on us unawares; Be not drunk with Wine of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſures and cares, wherein is exceſſe, but be we filled with the Spirit, ſpeaking to our ſelves, and one another in Pſalms, Hymns,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32511:24"/>
and ſpiritual ſongs, &amp;c. not forſaking the aſſembling of our ſelves together as the manner of ſome it, but exhorting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and ſo much the more, as wee ſee the day approaching, and for our encouragement herein, that we be not ſlothful, but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of them, who through faith and patience, do already in Spirit inherit the promiſes; Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright; look upon him in the light of Gods teſtimonie, there you ſhall ſee, <hi>That the end of that man is peace;</hi> And this brings us to the laſt inſtruction.</p>
            <p>3 That even in theſe ſad judgements to the ſurvivers, there is ſpecial mercy, and choice bleſſedneſſe to thoſe ſo taken away, and that to be conſidered alſo. They are taken away from the evil, or as we read it from the evil to come.</p>
            <p>1 They are then taken away from, and do depart out of the fleſh, in its weak and corruptible ſtate, out of a vile, or wretched bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that had ſin in it to be ſtriven againſt, as well as death upon it, <hi>A law in the members warring againſt the law of the minde;</hi> And ſhall not again return to it, until it ſhall be renewed, or given them in a new glorious and incorruptible ſtate, in the firſt reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>2 They are then taken from an evil generation, that was continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vexing their righteous ſouls, with their unlawful and ungodly doctrines, and practiſes, and ſo from all Satans temptations, and batteries; the accuſer of our brethren is caſt down from Heaven, hee cannot reach the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, which are with Jeſus, and have finiſhed their warfare, their end is peace.</p>
            <p>3 They are taken from the evil, and judgements to come, as <hi>Lot</hi> was pluckt out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> that they may bee out of danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing defiled with the ſins, procuring ſuch judgements, that ſo they may not partake with them of their plagues, yea, that they may no longer plead for ſparing, and diverting ſuch judgements. Oh heavy judgement to the ſurvivers, yet therein the dead are bleſſed. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord from henceforth,</hi> yea ſaith the Spirit, <hi>that they may reſt from their labours, combates, and dangers;</hi> and their works follow them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1 This conſideration inſtructs us, that while they are in theſe mortal bodies, they are not taken away from the evil, though
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32511:25"/>
through grace delivered, kept, and daily getting eſcape from the pollutions and intanglements of it, and victory in the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al combate, yet they have ſin in them, as a Law in the members, to ſtrive againſt, even unto blood, to death, and that continual lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them captive, though they minding the things of the Spirit, in the light and power of the grace vouchſafed, are not led cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive by it; yea hitherto they have not attained, neither are they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, they have not yet apprehended, or laid hold of that for which they are apprehended of Chriſt Jeſus, but are preſſing on to it, expecting the full injoyment in ſoul and body in that bleſſed and firſt reſurrection; in the mean time, in death they are taken away from the evil, but not before, though in a ſenſe they are ſaid to be perfect, or upright ones, that have their hearts fixed to ſeek righteouſneſſe in Jeſus, though much weakneſſe and ſinfulneſſe be yet found in them; they are perfect, as oppoſed to waveringneſſe, or double-mindedneſſe, and ſo in the way of righteouſneſſe, in which is life, and light increaſing to the perfect day; but in this day, not arrived at their journies end, not perfect as to attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but ſtill ſtriving againſt ſin in themſelves, as well as againſt it in others, and ſo have fightings within, and fightings without, as alſo they are groaning under the burden of thoſe weakneſſes, and that death that is yet upon them, and in a ſenſe raigning over them.</p>
            <p>This ſhould teach us, not to be ſecure, or ſleep as do others, but to be watchful, and take heed to our ſelves, leſt at any time ſin get advantage over us, and we be hardened through the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it; left at any time we be overcharged with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe, and cares of this life, and ſo that day come on us unawates; <hi>Put wee on the whole Armour of God, that wee may be able to ſtand in this evil day, Heb.</hi> 3. 12, 13. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 34. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh,</hi> 1. 8, - 10. with <hi>chap.</hi> 2. 1.</p>
            <p>2 The dead that dye in the Lord, being then taken away from the evil; it mindes us. That the Lord knoweth how to deliver the godly out of temptation, and to reſerve the unjuſt unto the day of Judgement, to be puniſhed, that ſo we may now look to the Lord, and wait for the God of our ſalvation, as <hi>Micah.</hi> 7. 7, - 9. In his hand are all our times, and wayes, and with him iſ wiſdome, ſtrength, and faithfulneſſe, to deliver us from the evil of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32511:25"/>
temptations while yet we are left among them; and if hee ſee them too heavie for us, he will either deliver us out, or command reſtraint to the remainder of them, that might not tend to his praiſe in our profit, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76. 9, 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9.</p>
            <p>3 This conſideration alſo is an Antidote againſt immoderate mourning for them that ſleep in Jeſus, as thoſe without hope, it ſpeaks to all the ſurviving Brethren of ſuch in the faith, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Jeſus, that they have not loſt, but for the preſent parted with ſuch their Brethren, and helpers of their faith and joy, that they may enjoy them in a farre better manner for ever; when the Lord comes, he will bring them againe with him, in the meane time they are taken away from the evil, for which we have cauſe to rejoyce on their behalf; and for our owne parts that are left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind for a while, we know not how little a while that may be, it cannot be long; and this alſo we know, <hi>He that ſpared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all,</hi> he abides or dwells in him, <hi>whom alſo he hath raiſed from the dead,</hi> to ſupport and help us: <hi>through him we ſhall doe valiantly, it is he that treadeth down our enemies, yea he will with his Son give us all things;</hi> he doth and will keep us by his power, or powerful Goſpel through faith, to the Salvation now ready to be revealed in the laſt time, that we may alſo finiſh our courſe with joy, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60. 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 16, 17. &amp; 8. 32. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5.</p>
            <p>4 Let this laſt conſideration be of this further and general uſe to us all, ſeeing the righteous hath hope in his death, and the end of that man is peace; ſeek righteouſneſs, and ſeek it in the Lord, ſeek it by faith in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Seek the Lord while he may be found, and call upon him while he is near; we pray you, in Chriſts ſtead, be yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God;</hi> and as motives to it, conſider, 1. <hi>He hath made his Son that knew no ſin to be ſin, and a curſe for us, that wee might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him.</hi> Conſider how great things he hath done for you, in and through the cutting off the Meſſiah, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 24. 16 that he might be feared by you.</p>
            <p>1 Therein, by executing the Judgement of this world on him, (<hi>as Joh.</hi> 12. 31) he hath finiſhed the tranſgreſſion (that one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and diſobedience that brought in Sin and death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12 - 18.) and made an end of the ſins that came in meerly thereby, the guilt of all the ſin, and filthineſs of the nature thence naturally, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32511:26"/>
neceſſarily derived, Jeſus Chriſt hath by himſelf purged or taken away from before the Father, and ſo finiſhed and made an end of it in the Court, he being taken from the Priſon, and from the Judgement therefore laid on him, ſo that the Father will require no more paiments of that Debt, nor goe to Law or Judgement with men, according to that rule of Judgement; but hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all Judgement to the Son, that all men ſhould honour the Son as the Saviour and Redeemer, the Abolliſher of their death, and Deliverer of them from the curſe of the Law, even with the Same ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as they honour the Father, as the great Creator of them all, acknowledging the Redemption wrought, and his Power over them as <hi>Lord</hi> and Saviour, by means of death to bee of the ſame latitude, that ſo though ſin be in them, and death upon them, at the fruit of that firſt Tranſgreſſion, yet the ſting thereof, which is the Wrath of God, on that account due, the Curſe of the Law being ſuffered, and taken out by Chriſt, no man ſhall periſh for ever in or by that ſimply; neither remains it as an Iron barre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and them; no man is neceſſarily kept out from God by that ſinfulneſs and death yet remaining on them, but may come to God by Chriſt the Mediator, in whom the enmity is ſlaine, the peace made, and ſo the door opened, and way made clear, and the grace of God bringing Salvation to them through it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 23, 24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 22, 23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. 15, 16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 16. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 20. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11.</p>
            <p>2 Yea therein by making his Soul an offering for our ſin, and cauſing him to bear our ſins in his owne Body to the Tree, and in the vertue there of he hath made reconciliation for iniquity, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation, Purgation, or Sin-offering for the taking away the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſins of the people, and brought in everlaſting Righteouſneſs, the Works which the Father gave him to doe on earth, being once actually finiſhed in that perſon, the Sacrifice of his owne Body, perfected through ſufferings once offered, is of everlaſting value and vertue with the Father for us, even for the taking away the ſins of the world, and for the holding open the door of Life, and procuring the continuance of Mercies even to the rebellious, that the Lord might dwell among them; as well as likewiſe for the continual covering, and preſenting compleat, and ſpotleſs before
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32511:26"/>
the Father, all that are found in it, and for the perfecting what concerns them, God hath ſet him forth in the infinite vertue of that his perfect Righteouſneſs, and Sacrifice, a ſtanding Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, not for our ſins only that through grace beleeve, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world, that through him hee might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his righteouſneſs, in exerciſing patience, and forbearance to Rebells during the day of his grace, and patience, and that is while it is due time; and in juſtifying <hi>whoſoever through his Name beleeveth in him,</hi> that being juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption in Chriſt, they might be waſhed, ſanctified, and made Heirs in the vertues and influences of the ſame everlaſting righteouſneſs, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 25, 26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25 - 27. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 1, 2. ſo that though thoſe iniquities, or unrighteouſneſſes, in which when the light and power of the grace of God is bringing Salvation, and comes nigh to men leading to repentance, lifting up the yoke, then men cloſe their eyes, and harden their hearts, and chuſe darkneſs rather, becauſe their deeds are evil. Though I ſay, ſins of this nature be not finiſhed, or made an end of in the Court, as was ſaid of the fore-mentioned, but are detained in Heaven againſt men while they abide in them, they being of a new nature, and ſuch as were not, nor could have had being in the world, if there had not been peace made for them, and that alſo preached to them, even by his Spirit to their ſpirits (as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 19, 20.) <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 22 - 24. they provoke new wrath, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides over men while they continue in them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 18, 19, 36. and will end in a ſecond death, if perſiſted in till finiſhed by them; yet there is Reconciliation, and Propitiation made in the vertues of his Blood, or being cut off by death even for ſins of this nature, ſo that by means of that Death, which was for the redemption of the Tranſgreſſions under the firſt Teſtament, in the infinite and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding vertue of that Bloud, he is the Mediator between God and men, and maketh interceſſion for the Tranſgreſſors, yea hee hath received power and authority in the Name of the Father, to procure and give forbearance to Rebells, during his pleaſure; <hi>hee hath the Keys of</hi> David, <hi>he opens and no man ſhuts, hee ſhuts and no man opens, he hath received gifts for men</hi> (yea for the rebellious alſo) obſerve that additional clauſe, and the inſtruction in it, That he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32511:27"/>
not only gifts for men, as men and ſinners from <hi>Adam</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, but for the rebellious alſo, that the Lord God might dwell among them. And ſo alſo to give through his Name for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs even of all ſins paſt, to whoſoever through this grace, ſeeth and beleeveth on him, as well as always to preſent them accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the preſence of God in himſelf, in the vertue of that his perfect and everlaſting righteouſneſs, yea they have righteouſneſs and ſtrength in the Lord anſwering to all their needs, weakneſs, and nakedneſs for their covering in the preſence of God, and that they may be filled with the fruites of it, in the Lord ſhall all the ſeed of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> all the generation of ſeekers of Gods Name, and face in Chriſt be juſtified, and ſhall glory; therefore ſaith he, <hi>Look unto me, and be yee ſaved all the ends of the earth, for I am a juſt God, and a Saviour;</hi> and his righteouſneſs is an everlaſting righteouſneſs, and ſhall never be aboliſhed, however men fight againſt it.</p>
            <p>3 Therein he hath ſealed, or confirmed the Viſion, and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of bringing forth bleſſing in <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed to all Nations, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Son Jeſus, as raiſed from the Dead, for a Witneſs to the people, a Leader, and Commander to the people, a Light to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and his Salvation to the ends of the earth, <hi>Gen. 22. 18. Gal. 3. 8 - 13. Iſa. 42. &amp; 49. &amp; 55. 3 - 5. Acts 2. &amp; 13.</hi> for bee hath now made the man Chriſt Jeſus, in the Name and Majeſty of God, a teſtimony to men, the Light of the world, to bee teſtified to them in their ſeveral Ages, and in due time having anoynted the moſt Holy, even that moſt holy Body, the Perſonal Body of Chriſt, through ſufferings glorified with the Fathers owne ſelfe, the glory he had with him as the eternal Son of God before the World was, with the vertue of whoſe Bloud, the Heavens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were ſprinkled, that Grace and Truth might thence come forth to us, <hi>It hath therefore pleaſed the Father that in him ſhould all fulneſſe dwell, even the fulneſſe of the God-head bodily<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that of his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe we might all receive, for the opening our eyes, and turning us from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan to God, that we might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive forgiveneſſe of ſins, and inheritance among them that are ſanctified by faith in him;</hi> Now Jeſus Chriſt in his Perſonal miniſtration on earth, was a Miniſter of the Circumciſion, yea after his Aſcenſion the firſt pouring out of the Holy Ghoſt, bringing and opening
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32511:27"/>
the teſtimony of Jeſus as the Works are finiſhed in his Body was upon his Apoſtles, and Diſciples, that were all of the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and by them it was firſt to be preached to the Circumciſion, and after to all Nations for the obedience of faith. Now this his being a Miniſter of the Circumciſion, was to confirme the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the Fathers, and that in the confirmation of them, and in the grace ſo coming forth in <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, and confirmed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Family, and from thence coming forth to the Nations, the Gentiles might glorifie God for his mercy, as it is written; <hi>For this cauſe I will confeſſe to thee among the Gentiles, &amp;c.</hi> Rom. 15. 8, 9. And this may anſwer to his confirming the Covenant with many for one week, the laſt of the Seventy, in the midſt of which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was cut off, and did therein prepare, and through thoſe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings himſelf was perfected that everlaſting Sacrifice, in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in of which, the Typical Sacrifice and Oblation did ceaſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, or ſoon after the third day, or year of his being manifeſted to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſhewing himſelf in his Perſonal Miniſtration as the Son of God, the Saviour of the World, and ſo in the midſt of the week he was cut off, and through ſufferings made perfect, <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 32, 33. and in a like time after, the revelation of the myſtery out of the Scriptures of the Prophets was come forth fully and confirmed in them, and by them, according to the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the everlaſting God, given forth for obedience to the ſaith among all Nations, ſo that the Lord Jeſus in that his moſt holy Body, being made perfect through ſufferings, is the anoynted Prince and Saviour, for to give us repentance, and forgiveneſs of ſins; and he hath confirmed the Promiſes to the Fathers, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth the teſtimony and revelation of himſelf, and the Fathers glory in him, in full, and as it muſt ſtand till his Second appearing; At which Great Day, all the things behind ſhall even ſo bee ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, as declared in this diſpenſation of the fulneſs of times; in the meane time, <hi>God hath ſpoken to us in theſe last dayes by his Son,</hi> and in, and with, and according to this word is the influence of the light and power of his Spirit poured out on all Fleſh, on all the Nations, reproving the World, and leading Beleevers into all truth, the Father having glorified him for the calling the Nations in the preaching peace to them, by vertue of the peace made for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32511:28"/>
them by his bloud, <hi>Iſa. 55. 4, 5. Matthew 28. 18, 19. 1 Tim.</hi> 2. 5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p>2 In and with this conſideration of the great things he hath done: Rich proviſion of all things pertaining to life and godlineſs in him for us; behold him alſo in his faithfulneſs, in all his Work, and Office appointed him, it is according as it hath been manifeſted in that which he hath already done, therefore that to be remembred as a ſtanding witneſs of it, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 50. 4, 5, to the end; ſo <hi>Hebrews</hi> 12. 2. he that failed not in that, will not fail in any thing that he is appointed, and impowred to, for us in the vertues of that, either in his appearing in the preſence of God for us, or in the Name of the Father, giving good things to us, that through him we might be ſaved.</p>
            <p>See alſo the Fathers face in his, <hi>Good and upright is the Lord, therefore will be teach ſinners in the way;</hi> and then it follows, <hi>The meek,</hi> that is, thoſe ſinners that in his firſt and preventing teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are melted, and turne in the light and power of his reproofs, thoſe <hi>will he guide in judgement,</hi> and further teach his way, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 25. 8, 9. like that, <hi>John</hi> 16. 8, 9, 10 - 13. he fails not, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. but makes his Judgements as the Light that goeth forth, he is all the day long, while by any means he is calling to behold him, ſtretching out his hand, <hi>Iſaiah 65. 1, 2. Hoſea</hi> 6. 5, 6, 7. his goodneſs is leading to Repentance, even thoſe that are not led by it, <hi>Romans 2. 4, 5. Iſaiah 48. 17, 18. Pſalm</hi> 81. He is drawing with the cords of a man, the demonſtrations of a Saviour in a body prepared for him, through ſufferings made perfect, and glorified with the Fathers owne ſelf, and with he bands of love, the diſplayings of his love, and glory in that face of Chriſt, and therein lifting up the yoke of thraldome naturally on the <hi>Jewes,</hi> while he ſets meat before them, and this, even to ſuch as break his bands, and caſt away his cords from them, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 11. <hi>John 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14, 15, 16. Pſalm 2. Jeremy 5. 5. Zach. 7. 11, 12. Ezek. 24. 11. 13. Pſalm</hi> 81. and in turning at his reproof, he will pour out his Spirit further, and make known his words, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 1. 23. hee hath now no pleaſure in the death of any Sinner, yea behold, he ſtands ready to accept of all commers, <hi>And in every Nation, he that feareth God, and worketh Righteouſneſſe is accepted with him;</hi> to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32511:28"/>
               <hi>him give give the Prophets Witneſſe, that through his Name, whoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever beleeveth in him ſhall receive remiſſion of ſins; and the end of that man is peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider alſo as further Motives to preſs us to haſte, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in Learning Righteouſneſſe, the preſent opportunity only is ours, wherefore the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>To day if yee will hear his voyce, harden not your hearts;</hi> If once the good man of the Houſe (that by ſuch Providences, as is the ſubject of this Diſcourſe, appears as riſing up, if once he) bee riſen up, and have ſhut the door againſt any of us, it will then be too late. And this alſo, wee know wee muſt all dye, and doe ſee that the natural life is a very Bubble, preſently broken by the leaſt blaſt of God; and the gathering time terminates with that at fartheſt. After death, the Judgement ſhall bee accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the things now done in the Body, good or evil, according to the rule of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Let all move us to conſider, and receive inſtruction while it is to day, learn Righteouſneſſe by his Judgements, and for our direction herein, Hee hath ſhewed thee O man what is good; and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to doe juſtly, in receiving his Teſtimony concerning Chriſt, and as that gives ground, perſwades, and ſtrengthens in the ſupernatural Light and Power with which it is evidenced and made nigh thee, ſo through it beleeving on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, as <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> 4. &amp; 10. to love mercy, accept, receive, and drink downe the mercy and pitty of God to man-ward, as manifeſted in and through Chriſt bringing Salvation (as <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6. 6. with <hi>Matth.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 13.) reject not the grace of God in Chriſt, the love of the Truth that comes to ſave your ſouls; and walk humbly with thy God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging our owne vileneſſe, wretchedneſſe, and deadneſſe in ſins and treſpaſſes, aſcribing Righteouſneſſe to our Maker, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sentence of Death in our ſelves, that wee may learn to truſt in him that raiſeth the Dead; lift not up our imaginations, high thoughts, or purpoſes, againſt the evidence and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt, the inſtructions, reproofs, and requirings of that; <hi>Murmur not among your ſelves, but with meekneſſe receive the ingrafted word that is able to ſave your ſouls, and in the light and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32511:29"/>
ſtrength of it, be yee doers of it in all the fruites of Righteouſneſſe, Juſtice, Mercy, and humility in your whole demeanour towards God and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that Grace of God that brings Salvation to all men, hath appeared, teaching us, that denying ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world, looking for that bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hope, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lords voyce crieth unto the City, the man of wiſdome ſhall ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> name, hear yee the Rod, and who hath appointed it,</hi> Mich. 6. 8, 9.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2 l. 1. r. ſignificant. p. 6. l. 26. adde, he is guilty of all p. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> jawer. p. 19. l. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. for in. r. from. p. 17. l. 1. r. beleeve, p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7. l. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> l. 23. adde the, p. 48. l. 29. r. jawes:</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
